<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://lamaquinadeturing.su/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://lamaquinadeturing.su/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-09-10T21:04:19+00:00</updated><id>https://lamaquinadeturing.su/feed.xml</id><title type="html">La màquina de Turing</title><subtitle>cat /dev/random</subtitle><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Simple Sabotage Field Manual</title><link href="https://lamaquinadeturing.su/en/2024/09/simple-sabotage-field-manual/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Simple Sabotage Field Manual" /><published>2024-09-08T17:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-08T17:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://lamaquinadeturing.su/en/2024/09/simple-sabotage-field-manual</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lamaquinadeturing.su/en/2024/09/simple-sabotage-field-manual/"><![CDATA[<p><em>The</em> <a href="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Simple_Sabotage_Field_Manual" class="link-wikipedia">Simple Sabotage Field Manual</a> <em>was a collection of simple sabotage techniques gathered by the</em> Office of Strategic Services <em>(predecessor of the CIA) during World War II to be distributed among workers in enemy countries and disrupt their industry and military.</em></p>

<p><em>Despite being used in 1944, many of its methods will be familiar to 21st century readers. Notably, some techniques come from observing inefficiencies that happen in many organizations “even under normal conditions”, which makes many people inadvertently act as “saboteurs”. For example, by “bringing up irrelevant issues as frequently as possible” or “referring back to matters decided upon at the last meeting and attempting to re-open the question”.</em></p>

<p><em>Erik Bernhardsson adapted it to software development in his <a href="https://erikbern.com/2023/12/13/simple-sabotage-for-software.html" class="link-external">Simple sabotage for software</a>.</em></p>

<hr>

<div class="textright">
<p class="textleft" style="display: inline-block">Office of Strategic Services<br>
Washington, D. C.<br>
17 January 1944</p>
</div>

<p>This Simple Sabotage Field Manual — Strategic Services (Provisional) — is published for the information and guidance of all concerned and will be used as the basic doctrine for Strategic Services training for this subject.</p>

<p>The contents of this Manual should be carefully controlled and should not be allowed to come into unauthorized hands.</p>

<p>The instructions may be placed in separate pamphlets or leaflets according to categories of operations but should be distributed with care and not broadly. They should be used as a basis of radio broadcasts only for local and special cases and as directed by the theater commander.</p>

<p>AR 380-5, pertaining to handling of secret documents, will be complied with in the handling of this Manual.</p>

<p class="textcenter"><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_J._Donovan" class="link-wikipedia">William J. Donovan</a><br>
Director</p>

<h2 class="no-toc" id="heading-contents">Contents</h2>

<div class="toc">
<p id="toc-1" class="toc toc-h2"><a href="#heading-1-introduction">1. Introduction</a></p>
<p id="toc-2" class="toc toc-h2"><a href="#heading-2-possible-effects">2. Possible Effects</a></p>
<p id="toc-3" class="toc toc-h2"><a href="#heading-3-motivating-the-saboteur">3. Motivating The Saboteur</a></p>
<p id="toc-4" class="toc toc-h2"><a href="#heading-4-tools-targets-and-timing">4. Tools, Targets, And Timing</a></p>
<p id="toc-5" class="toc toc-h2"><a href="#heading-5-specific-suggestions-for-simple-sabotage">5. Specific Suggestions For Simple Sabotage</a></p>
</div>

<h2 id="heading-1-introduction" class="heading">1. Introduction <a href="#toc-1" class="toc-back-link">↩</a>
</h2>

<p>The purpose of this paper is to characterize simple sabotage, to outline its possible effects, and to present suggestions for inciting and executing it.</p>

<p>Sabotage varies from highly technical coup de main acts that require detailed planning and the use of specially-trained operatives, to innumerable simple acts which the ordinary individual citizen-saboteur can perform. This paper is primarily concerned with the latter type. Simple sabotage does not require specially prepared tools or equipment; it is executed by an ordinary citizen who may or may not act individually and without the necessity for active connection with an organized group; and it is carried out in such a way as to involve a minimum danger of injury, detection, and reprisal.</p>

<p>Where destruction is involved, the weapons of the citizen-saboteur are salt, nails, candles, pebbles, thread, or any other materials he might normally be expected to possess as a householder or as a worker in his particular occupation. His arsenal is the kitchen shelf, the trash pile, his own usual kit of tools and supplies. The targets of his sabotage are usually objects to which he has normal and inconspicuous access in everyday life.</p>

<p>A second type of simple sabotage requires no destructive tools whatsoever and produces physical damage, if any, by highly indirect means. It is based on universal opportunities to make faulty decisions, to adopt a noncooperative attitude, and to induce others to follow suit. Making a faulty decision may be simply a matter of placing tools in one spot instead of another. A non-cooperative attitude may involve nothing more than creating an unpleasant situation among one’s fellow workers, engaging in bickerings, or displaying surliness and stupidity.</p>

<p>This type of activity, sometimes referred to as the “human element,” is frequently responsible for accidents, delays, and general obstruction even under normal conditions. The potential saboteur should discover what types of faulty decisions and the operations are normally found in this kind of work and should then devise his sabotage so as to enlarge that “margin for error.”</p>

<h2 id="heading-2-possible-effects" class="heading">2. Possible Effects <a href="#toc-2" class="toc-back-link">↩</a>
</h2>

<p>Acts of simple sabotage are occurring throughout Europe. An effort should be made to add to their efficiency, lessen their detectability, and increase their number. Acts of simple sabotage, multiplied by thousands of citizen-saboteurs, can be an effective weapon against the enemy. Slashing tires, draining fuel tanks, starting fires, starting arguments, acting stupidly, short-circuiting electric systems, abrading machine parts will waste materials, manpower, and time. Occurring on a wide scale, simple sabotage will be a constant and tangible drag on the war effort of the enemy.</p>

<p>Simple sabotage may also have secondary results of more or less value. Widespread practice of simple sabotage will harass and demoralize enemy administrators and police. Further, success may embolden the citizen-saboteur eventually to find colleagues who can assist him in sabotage of greater dimensions. Finally, the very practice of simple sabotage by natives in enemy or occupied territory may make these individuals identify themselves actively with the United Nations war effort, and encourage them to assist openly in periods of Allied invasion and occupation.</p>

<h2 id="heading-3-motivating-the-saboteur" class="heading">3. Motivating The Saboteur <a href="#toc-3" class="toc-back-link">↩</a>
</h2>

<p>To incite the citizen to the active practice of simple sabotage and to keep him practicing that sabotage over sustained periods is a special problem.</p>

<p>Simple sabotage is often an act which the citizen performs according to his own initiative and inclination. Acts of destruction do not bring him any personal gain and may be completely foreign to his habitually conservationist attitude toward materials and tools. Purposeful stupidity is contrary to human nature. He frequently needs pressure, stimulation or assurance, and information and suggestions regarding feasible methods of simple sabotage.</p>

<h3 id="heading-1-personal-motives">(1) Personal Motives</h3>

<p>(a) The ordinary citizen very probably has no immediate personal motive for committing simple sabotage. Instead, he must be made to anticipate indirect personal gain, such as might come with enemy evacuation or destruction of the ruling government group. Gains should be stated as specifically as possible for the area addressed: simple sabotage will hasten the day when Commissioner X and his deputies Y and Z will be thrown out, when particularly obnoxious decrees and restrictions will be abolished, when food will arrive, and so on. Abstract verbalizations about personal liberty, freedom of the press, and so on, will not be convincing in most parts of the world. In many areas they will not even be comprehensible.</p>

<p>(b) Since the effect of his own acts is limited, the saboteur may become discouraged unless he feels that he is a member of a large, though unseen, group of saboteurs operating against the enemy or the government of his own country and elsewhere. This can be conveyed indirectly: suggestions which he reads and hears can include observations that a particular technique has been successful in this or that district. Even if the technique is not applicable to his surroundings, another’s success will encourage him to attempt similar acts. It also can be conveyed directly: statements praising the effectiveness of simple sabotage can be contrived which will be published by white radio, freedom stations, and the subversive press. Estimates of the proportion of the population engaged in sabotage can be disseminated. Instances of successful sabotage already are being broadcast by white radio and freedom stations, and this should be continued and expanded where compatible with security.</p>

<p>(c) More important than (a) or (b) would be to create a situation in which the citizen-saboteur acquires a sense of responsibility and begins to educate others in simple sabotage.</p>

<h3 id="heading-2-encouraging-destructiveness">(2) Encouraging Destructiveness</h3>

<p>It should be pointed out to the saboteur where the circumstances are suitable, that he is acting in self-defense against the enemy, or retaliating against the enemy for other acts of destruction. A reasonable amount of humor in the presentation of suggestions for simple sabotage will relax tensions of fear.</p>

<p>(a) The saboteur may have to reverse his thinking, and he should be told this in so many words. Where he formerly thought of keeping his tools sharp, he should now let them grow dull; surfaces that formerly were lubricated now should be sanded; normally diligent, he should now be lazy and careless; and so on. Once he is encouraged to think backwards about himself and the objects of his everyday life, the saboteur will see many opportunities in his immediate environment which cannot possibly be seen from a distance. A state of mind should be encouraged that anything can be sabotaged.</p>

<p>(b) Among the potential citizen-saboteurs who are to engage in physical destruction, two extreme types may be distinguished. On the one hand, there is the man who is not technically trained and employed. This man needs specific suggestions as to what he can and should destroy as well as details regarding the tools by means of which destruction is accomplished.</p>

<p>(c) At the other extreme is the man who is a technician, such as a lathe operator or an automobile mechanic. Presumably this man would be able to devise methods of simple sabotage which would be appropriate to his own facilities. However, this man needs to be stimulated to re-orient his thinking in the direction of destruction. Specific examples, which need not be from his own field, should accomplish this.</p>

<p>(d) Various media may be used to disseminate suggestions and information regarding simple sabotage. Among the media which may be used, as the immediate situation dictates, are: freedom stations or radio false (unreadable) broadcasts or leaflets may be directed toward specific geographic or occupational areas, or they may be general in scope. Finally, agents may be trained in the art of simple sabotage, in anticipation of a time when they may be able to communicate this information directly.</p>

<h3 id="heading-3-safety-measures">(3) Safety Measures</h3>

<p>(a) The amount of activity carried on by the saboteur will be governed not only by the number of opportunities he sees, but also by the amount of danger he feels. Bad news travels fast, and simple sabotage will be discouraged if too many simple saboteurs are arrested.</p>

<p>(b) It should not be difficult to prepare leaflets and other media for the saboteur about the choice of weapons, time, and targets which will insure the saboteur against detection and retaliation. Among such suggestions might be the following:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Use materials which appear to be innocent. A knife or a nail file can be carried normally on your person; either is a multi-purpose instrument for creating damage. Matches, pebbles, hair, salt, nails, and dozens of other destructive agents can be carried or kept in your living quarters without exciting any suspicion whatever. If you are a worker in a particular trade or industry you can easily carry and keep such things as wrenches, hammers, emery paper, and the like.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Try to commit acts for which large numbers of people could be responsible. For instance, if you blow out the wiring in a factory at a central fire box, almost anyone could have done it. On-the-street sabotage after dark, such as you might be able to carry out against a military car or truck, is another example of an act for which it would be impossible to blame you.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Do not be afraid to commit acts for which you might be blamed directly, so long as you do so rarely, and as long as you have a plausible excuse: you dropped your wrench across an electric circuit because an air raid had kept you up the night before and you were half-dozing at work. Always be profuse in your apologies. Frequently you can “get away” with such acts under the cover of pretending stupidity, ignorance, over-caution, fear of being suspected of sabotage, or weakness and dullness due to undernourishment.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>After you have committed an act of easy sabotage, resist any temptation to wait around and see what happens. Loiterers arouse suspicion. Of course, there are circumstances when it would be suspicious for you to leave. If you commit sabotage on your job, you should naturally stay at your work.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<h2 id="heading-4-tools-targets-and-timing" class="heading">4. Tools, Targets, And Timing <a href="#toc-4" class="toc-back-link">↩</a>
</h2>

<p>The citizen-saboteur cannot be closely controlled. Nor is it reasonable to expect that simple sabotage can be precisely concentrated on specific types of target according to the requirements of a concrete military situation. Attempts to control simple sabotage according to developing military factors, moreover, might provide the enemy with intelligence of more or less value in anticipating the date and area of notably intensified or notably slackened military activity.</p>

<p>Sabotage suggestions, of course, should be adapted to fit the area where they are to be practiced. Target priorities for general types of situations likewise can be specified, for emphasis at the proper time by the underground press, freedom stations, and cooperating propaganda.</p>

<h3 id="heading-1-under-general-conditions">(1) Under General Conditions</h3>

<p>(a) Simple sabotage is more than malicious mischief, and it should always consist of acts whose results will be detrimental to the materials and manpower of the enemy.</p>

<p>(b) The saboteur should be ingenious in using his every-day equipment. All sorts of weapons will present themselves if he looks at his surroundings in a different light. For example, emery dust —a powerful weapon— may at first seem unobtainable, but if the saboteur were to pulverize an emery knife sharpener or emery wheel with a hammer, he would find himself with a plentiful supply.</p>

<p>(c) The saboteur should never attack targets beyond his capacity or the capacity of his instruments. An inexperienced person should not, for example, attempt to use explosives, but should confine himself to the use of matches or other familiar weapons.</p>

<p>(d) The saboteur should try to damage only objects and materials known to be in use by the enemy or to be destined for early use by the enemy. It will be safe for him to assume that almost any product of heavy industry is destined for enemy use, and that the most efficient fuels and lubricants also are destined for enemy use. Without special knowledge, however, it would be undesirable for him to attempt destruction of food crops or food products.</p>

<p>(e) Although the citizen-saboteur may rarely have access to military objects, he should give these preference above all others.</p>

<h3 id="heading-2-prior-to-a-military-offensive">(2) Prior to a Military Offensive</h3>

<p>During periods which are quiescent in a military sense, such emphasis as can be given to simple sabotage might well center on industrial production, to lessen the flow of materials and equipment to the enemy. Slashing a rubber tire on an Army truck may be an act of value; spoiling a batch of rubber in the production plant is an act of still more value.</p>

<h3 id="heading-3-during-a-military-offensive">(3) During a Military Offensive</h3>

<p>(a) Most significant sabotage for an area which is, or is soon destined to be, a theater of combat operations is that whose effects will be direct and immediate. Even if the effects are relatively minor and localized, this type of sabotage is to be preferred to activities whose effects, while widespread, are indirect and delayed.</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>The saboteur should be encouraged to attack transportation facilities of all kinds.</p>

    <p>Among such facilities are roads, railroads, auto mobiles, trucks, motor-cycles, bicycles, trains, and trams.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Any communications facilities which can be used by the authorities to transmit instructions or morale material should be the objects of simple sabotage. These include telephone, telegraph and power systems, radio, newspapers, placards, and public notices.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Critical materials, valuable in themselves or necessary to the efficient functioning of transportation and communication, also should become targets for the citizen-saboteur. These may include oil, gasoline, tires, food, and water.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<h2 id="heading-5-specific-suggestions-for-simple-sabotage" class="heading">5. Specific Suggestions For Simple Sabotage <a href="#toc-5" class="toc-back-link">↩</a>
</h2>

<p>It will not be possible to evaluate the desirability of simple sabotage in an area without having in mind rather specifically what individual acts and results are embraced by the definition of simple sabotage.</p>

<p>A listing of specific acts follows, classified according to types of target. This list is presented as a growing rather than a complete outline of the methods of simple sabotage. As new techniques are developed, or new fields explored, it will be elaborated and expanded.</p>

<h3 id="heading-1-buildings">(1) Buildings</h3>

<p>Warehouses, barracks, offices, hotels, and factory buildings are outstanding targets for simple sabotage. They are extremely susceptible to damage, especially by fire; they offer opportunities to such untrained people as janitors, charwomen, and casual visitors; and, when damaged, they present a relatively large handicap to the enemy.</p>

<p>(a) Fires can be started wherever there is an accumulation of inflammable material. Warehouses are obviously the most promising targets but incendiary sabotage need not be confined to them alone.</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Whenever possible, arrange to have the fire start after you have gone away. Use a candle and paper, combination, setting it as close as possible to the inflammable material you want to burn: From a sheet of paper, tear a strip three or four centimeters wide and wrap it around the base of the candle two or three times. Twist more sheets of paper into loose ropes and place them around the base of the candle. When the candle flame reaches the encircling strip, it will be ignited and in turn will ignite the surrounding paper. The size, heat, and duration of the resulting flame will depend on how much paper you use and how much of it you can cramp in a small space.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>With a flame of this kind, do not attempt to ignite any but rather inflammable materials, such as cotton sacking. To light more resistant materials, use a candle plus tightly rolled or twisted paper which has been soaked in gasoline. To create a briefer but even hotter flame, put celluloid such as you might find in an old comb, into a nest of plain or saturated paper which is to be fired by a candle.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>To make another type of simple fuse, soak one end of a piece of string in grease. Rub a generous pinch of gunpowder over the inch of string where greasy string meets clean string. Then ignite the clean end of the string. It will burn slowly without a flame i. much the same way that a cigarette burns) until it reaches the grease and gunpowder; it will then flare up suddenly. The grease-treated string will then burn with a flame. The same effect may be achieved by using matches instead of the grease and gunpowder. Run the string over the match heads, taking care that the string is not pressed or knotted. They too will produce a sudden flame. The advantage of this type of fuse is that string burns at a set speed. You can time your fire by the length and thickness of the string you chose.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Use a fuse such as; the ones suggested above to start a fire in an office after hours. The destruction of records and other types of documents would be a serious handicap to the enemy.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>In basements where waste is kept, janitors should accumulate oily and greasy waste. Such waste sometimes ignites spontaneously, but it can easily be lit with a cigarette or match. If you are a janitor on night duty, you can be the first to report the fire, but don’t report it too soon.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>A clean factory is not susceptible to fire, but a dirty one is. Workers should be careless with refuse and janitors should be inefficient in cleaning. If enough dirt and trash can be accumulated an otherwise fireproof building will become inflammable.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Where illuminating gas is used in a room which is vacant at night, shut the windows tightly, turn on the gas, and leave a candle burning in the room, closing the door tightly behind you. After a time, the gas will explode, and a fire may or may not follow.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>(b) Water and miscellaneous</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Ruin warehouse stock by setting the automatic sprinkler system to work. You can do this by tapping the sprinkler heads sharply with a hammer or by holding a match under them.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Forget to provide paper in toilets; put tightly rolled paper, hair, and other obstructions in the W. C. Saturate a sponge with a thick starch or sugar solution. Squeeze it tightly into a ball, wrap it with string, and dry. Remove the string when fully dried. The sponge will be in the form of a tight hard ball. Flush down a</p>

    <p>W. C. or otherwise introduce into a sewer line. The sponge will gradually expand to its normal size and plug the sewage system.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Put a coin beneath a bulb in a public building during the daytime, so that fuses will blow out when lights are turned on at night. The fuses themselves may be rendered ineffective by putting a coin behind them or loading them with heavy wire. Then a short-circuit may either start a fire, damage transformers, or blow out a central fuse which will interrupt distribution of electricity to a large area.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Jam paper, bits of wood, hairpins, and anything else that will fit, into the locks of all unguarded entrances to public buildings.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<h3 id="heading-2-industrial-production-manufacturing">(2) Industrial Production: Manufacturing</h3>

<p>(a) Tools</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Let cutting tools grow dull. They will be inefficient, will slow down production, and may damage the materials and parts you use them on.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Leave saws slightly twisted when you are not using them. After a while, they will break when used.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Using a very rapid stroke will wear out a file before its time. So will dragging a file in slow strokes under heavy pressure. Exert pressure on the backward stroke as well as the forward stroke.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Clean files by knocking them against the vise or the workpiece; they are easily broken this way.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Bits and drills will snap under heavy pressure.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>You can put a press punch out of order by putting in it more material than it is adjusted for — two blanks instead of one, for example.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Power-driven tools like pneumatic drills, riveters, and so on, are never efficient when dirty. Lubrication points and electric contacts can easily be fouled by normal accumulations of dirt or the insertion of foreign matter.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>(b) Oil and lubrication systems are not only vulnerable to easy sabotage, but are critical in every machine with moving parts. Sabotage of oil and lubrication will slow production or stop work entirely at strategic points in industrial processes.</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Put metal dust or filings, fine sand, ground glass, emery dust (get it by pounding up an emery knife sharpener) and similar hard, gritty substances directly into lubrication systems. They will scour smooth surfaces, ruining pistons, cylinder walls, shafts, and bearings. They will overheat and stop motors which will need overhauling, new parts, and extensive repairs. Such materials, if they are used, should be introduced into lubrication systems past any filters which otherwise would strain them out.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>You can cause wear on any machine by uncovering a filter system, poking a pencil or any other sharp object through the filter mesh, then covering it up again. Or, if you can dispose of it quickly, simply remove the filter.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>If you cannot get at the lubrication system or filter directly, you may be able to lessen the effectiveness of oil by diluting it in storage. In this case, almost any liquid will do which will thin the oil. A small amount of sulphuric acid, varnish, water-glass, or linseed oil will be especially effective.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Using a thin oil where a heavy oil is prescribed will break down a machine or heat up a moving shaft so that it will “freeze” and stop.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Put any clogging substance into lubrication systems or, if it will float, into stored oil. Twisted combings of human hair, pieces of string, dead insects, and many other common objects will be effective in stopping or hindering the flow of oil through feed lines and filters.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Under some circumstances, you may be able to destroy oil outright rather than interfere with its effectiveness, by removing stop-plugs from lubricating systems or by puncturing the drums and cans in which it is stored.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>(c) Cooling Systems</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>A water cooling system can be put out of commission in a fairly short time, with considerable damage to an engine or motor, if you put into it several pinches of hard grain, such as rice or wheat. They will swell up and choke the circulation of water, and the cooling system will have to be torn down to remove the obstruction. Sawdust or hair may also be used to clog a water cooling system.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>If very cold water is quickly introduced into the cooling system of an overheated motor, contraction and considerable strain on the engine housing will result. If you can repeat the treatment a few times, cracking and serious damage will result.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>You can ruin the effectiveness of an air cooling system by plugging dirt and waste into intake or exhaust valves. If a belt-run fan is used in the system, make a jagged cut at least half way through the belt; it will slip and finally part under strain and the motor will overheat.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>(d) Gasoline and Oil Fuel Tanks and fueling engines usually are accessible and easy to open. They afford a very vulnerable target for simple sabotage activities.</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Put several pinches of sawdust or hard grain, such as rice or wheat, into the fuel tank of a gasoline engine. The particles will choke a feed line so that the engine will stop. Some time will be required to discover the source of the trouble. Although they will be hard to get, crumbs of natural rubber, such as you might find in old rubber bands and pencil erasers, are also effective.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>If you can accumulate sugar, put it in the fuel tank of a gasoline engine. As it burns together with the gasoline, it will turn into a sticky mess which will completely mire the engine and necessitate extensive cleaning and repair. Honey and molasses are as good as sugar. Try to use about 75–100 grams for each 10 gallons of gasoline.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Other impurities which you can introduce into gasoline will cause rapid engine wear and eventual breakdown. Fine particles of pumice, sand, ground glass, and metal dust can easily be introduced into a gasoline tank. Be sure that the particles are very fine, so that they will be able to pass through the carburetor jet.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Water, urine, wine, or any other simple liquid you can get in reasonably large quantities will dilute gasoline fuel to a point where no combustion will occur in the cylinder and the engine will not move. One pint to 20 gallons of gasoline is sufficient. If salt water is used, it will cause corrosion and permanent motor damage.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>In the case of Diesel engines, put low flashpoint oil into the fuel tank; the engine will not move. If there already is proper oil in the tank when the wrong kind is added, the engine will only limp and sputter along.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Fuel lines to gasoline and oil engines frequently pass over the exhaust pipe. When the machine is at rest, you can stab a small hole in the fuel line and plug the hole with wax. As the engine runs and the exhaust tube becomes hot, the wax will be melted; fuel will drip onto the exhaust and a blaze will start.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>If you have access to a room where gasoline is stored, remember that gas vapor accumulating in a closed room will explode after a time if you leave a candle burning in the room. A good deal of evaporation, however, must occur from the gasoline tins into the air of the room. If removal of the tops of the tins does not expose enough gasoline to the air to ensure copious evaporation, you can open lightly constructed tins further with a knife, ice pick or sharpened nail file. Or puncture a tiny hole in the tank which will permit gasoline to leak out on the floor. This will greatly increase the rate of evaporation. Before you light your candle, be sure that windows are closed and the room is as air-tight as you can make it. If you can see that windows in a neighboring room are opened wide, you have a chance of setting a large fire which will not only destroy the gasoline but anything else nearby; when the gasoline explodes, the doors of the storage room will be blown open, a draft to the neighboring windows will be created which will whip up a fine conflagration.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>(e) Electric Motors</p>

<p>Electric motors (including dynamos) are more restricted than the targets so far discussed. They cannot be sabotaged easily or without risk of injury by unskilled persons who may otherwise have good opportunities for destruction.</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Set the rheostat to a high point of resistance in all types of electric motors. They will overheat and catch fire.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Adjust the overload relay to a very high value beyond the capacity of the motor. Then overload the motor to a point where it will overheat and break down.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Remember that dust, dirt, and moisture are enemies of electrical equipment. Spill dust and dirt onto the points where the wires in electric motors connect with terminals, and onto insulating parts. Inefficient transmission of current and, in some cases, short circuits will result. Wet generator motors to produce short circuits.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>“Accidentally” bruise the insulation on wire, loosen nuts on connections, make faulty splices and faulty connections in wiring, to waste electric current and reduce the power of electric motors.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Damage to commutators can reduce the power output or cause short circuiting in direct-current motors: Loosen or remove commutator holding rings. Sprinkle carbon, graphite, or metal dust on commutators. Put a little grease or oil at the contact points of commutators. Where commutator bars are close together bridge the gaps between them with metal dust, or sawtooth their edges with a chisel so that the teeth on adjoining bars meet or nearly meet and current can pass from one to the other.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Put a piece of finely grained emery paper half the size of a postage stamp in a place where it will wear away rotating brushes. The emery paper and the motor will be destroyed in the resulting fire.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Sprinkle carbon, graphite or metal dust on slip-rings so that the current will leak or short circuits will occur. When a motor is idle, nick the slip-rings with a chisel.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Cause motor stoppage or inefficiency by applying dust mixed with grease to the face of the armature so that it will not make proper contact.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>To overheat electric motors, mix sand with heavy grease and smear it between the stator and rotor, or wedge thin metal pieces between them. To prevent the efficient generation of current, put floor sweepings, oil, tar, or paint between them.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>In motors using three-phase current, deeply nick one of the lead-in wires with a knife or file when the machine is at rest, or replace one of the three fuses with a blown-out fuse. In the first case, the motor will stop after running awhile, and in the second, it will not start.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>(f) Transformers</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Transformers of the oil-filled type can be put out of commission if you pour water, salt water, machine-tool coolant, or kerosene into the oil tank.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>In air-cooled transformers, block the ventilation by piling debris around the transformer.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>In all types of transformers, throw carbon, graphite or metal dust over the outside bushings and other exposed electrical parts.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>(g) Turbines for the most part are heavily built, stoutly housed, and difficult of access. Their vulnerability to simple sabotage is very low.</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>After inspecting or repairing a hydro turbine, fasten the cover insecurely so that it will blow off and flood the plant with water. A loose cover on a steam turbine will cause it to leak and slow down.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>In water turbines, insert a large piece of scrap iron in the head of the penstock, just beyond the screening, so that water will carry the damaging material down to the plant equipment.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>When the steam line to a turbine is opened for repair, put pieces of scrap iron into it, to be blasted into the turbine machinery when steam is up again.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Create a leak in the line feeding oil to the turbine, so that oil will fall on the hot steam pipe and cause a fire.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>(h) Boilers</p>

<ol>
  <li>Reduce the efficiency of steam boilers any way you can. Put too much water in them to make them slow-starting, or keep the fire under them low to keep them inefficient. Let them dry and turn the fire up; they will crack and be ruined. An especially good trick is to keep putting limestone or water containing lime in the boiler; it will deposit lime on the bottom and sides. This deposit will provide very good insulation against heat; after enough of it has collected, the boiler will be completely worthless.</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="heading-3-production-metals">(3) Production. Metals</h3>

<p>(a) Iron and Steel</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Keep blast furnaces in a condition where they must be frequently shut down for repair. In making fire-proof bricks for the inner lining of blast furnaces, put in an extra proportion of tar so that they will wear out quickly and necessitate constant re-lining.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Make cores for casting so that they are filled with air bubbles and an imperfect cast results.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>See that the core in a mold is not properly supported, so that the core gives way or the casting is spoiled because of the incorrect position of the core.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>In tempering steel or iron, apply too much heat, so that the resulting bars and ingots are of poor quality.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>(b) Other Metals</p>

<p>No suggestions available.</p>

<h3 id="heading-4-production-mining-and-mineral-extraction">(4) Production: Mining and Mineral Extraction</h3>

<p>(a) Coal</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>A slight blow against your Davy oil lamp will extinguish it, and to light it again you will have to find a place where there is no fire damp. Take a long time looking for the place.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Blacksmiths who make pneumatic picks should not harden them properly, so that they will quickly grow dull.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>You can easily put your pneumatic pick out of order. Pour a small amount of water through the oil lever and your pick will stop working. Coal dust and improper lubrication will also put it out of order.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Weaken the chain that pulls the bucket conveyers carrying coal. A deep dent in the chain made with blows of a pick or shovel will cause it to part under normal strain. Once a chain breaks, normally or otherwise take your time about reporting the damage; be slow about taking the chain up for repairs and bringing it back down after repairs.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Derail mine cars by putting obstructions on the rails and in switch points. If possible, pick a gallery where coal cars have to pass each other, so that traffic will be snarled up.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Send up quantities of rock and other useless material with the coal.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<h3 id="heading-5-production-agriculture">(5) Production: Agriculture</h3>

<p>(a) Machinery</p>

<ol>
  <li>See par. 5 b. (2) (c), (d), (e).</li>
</ol>

<p>(b) Crops and livestock probably will be destroyed only in areas where there are large food surpluses or where the enemy (regime) is known to be requisitioning food.</p>

<ol>
  <li>Feed crops to livestock. Let crops harvest too early or too late. Spoil stores of grain, fruit and vegetables by soaking them in water so that they will rot. Spoil fruit and vegetables by leaving them in the sun.</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="heading-6-transportation-railways">(6) Transportation: Railways</h3>

<p>(a) Passengers</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Make train travel as inconvenient as possible for enemy personnel. Make mistakes in issuing train tickets, leaving portions of the journey uncovered by the ticket book; issue two tickets for the same seat in the train, so that an interesting argument will result; near train time, instead of issuing printed tickets write them out slowly by hand, prolonging the process until the train is nearly ready to leave or has left the station. On station bulletin boards announcing train arrivals and departures, see that false and misleading information is given about trains bound for enemy destinations.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>In trains bound for enemy destinations, attendants should make life as uncomfortable as possible for passengers. See that the food is especially bad, take up tickets after midnight, call all station stops very loudly during the night, handle baggage as noisily as possible during the night, and so on.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>See that the luggage of enemy personnel is mislaid or unloaded at the wrong stations.</p>

    <p>Switch address labels on enemy baggage.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Engineers should see that trains run slow or make unscheduled stops for plausible reasons.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>(b) Switches, Signals and Routing</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Exchange wires in switchboards containing signals and switches, so that they connect to the wrong terminals.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Loosen push-rods so that signal arms do not work; break signal lights; exchange the colored lenses on red and green lights.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Spread and spike switch points in the track so that they will not move, or place rocks or close-packed dirt between the switch points.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Sprinkle rock salt or ordinary salt profusely over the electrical connections of switch points and on the ground nearby. When it rains, the switch will be short-circuited.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>See that cars are put on the wrong trains. Remove the labels from cars needing repair and put them on cars in good order. Leave couplings between cars as loose as possible.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>(c) Road-beds and Open Track</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>On a curve, take the bolts out of the tie-plates connecting to sections of the outside rail, and scoop away the gravel, cinders, or dirt for a few feet on each side of the connecting joint.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>If by disconnecting the tie-plate at a joint and loosening sleeper nails on each side of the joint, it becomes possible to move a sections of rail, spread two sections of rail and drive a spike vertically between them.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>(d) Oil and Lubrication</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>See 5 b. (2) (b).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Squeeze lubricating pipes with pincers or dent them with hammers, so that the flow of oil is obstructed.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>(e) Cooling Systems</p>

<ol>
  <li>See 5 b (2) (c).</li>
</ol>

<p>(f) Gasoline and Oil Fuel</p>

<ol>
  <li>See 5 b (2) (d).</li>
</ol>

<p>(g) Electric Motors</p>

<ol>
  <li>See 5 b (2) (e) and (f).</li>
</ol>

<p>(h) Boilers</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>See 5 b (2) (h).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>After inspection put heavy oil or tar in the engines’ boilers, or put half a kilogram of soft soap into the water in the tender.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>(i) Brakes and Miscellaneous</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Engines should run at high speeds and use brakes excessively at curves and on downhill grades.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Punch holes in air-brake valves or water supply pipes.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>In the last car of a passenger train or or a front car of a freight, remove the wadding from a journal box and replace it with oily rags.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<h3 id="heading-7-transportation-automotive">(7) Transportation: Automotive</h3>

<p>(a) Roads. Damage to roads [(3) below] is slow, and therefore impractical as a D-day or near D-day activity.</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Change sign posts at intersections and forks; the enemy will go the wrong way and it may be miles before he discovers his mistakes.</p>

    <p>In areas where traffic is composed primarily of enemy autos, trucks, and motor convoys of various kinds remove danger signals from curves and intersections.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>When the enemy asks for directions, give him wrong information. Especially when enemy convoys are in the neighborhood, truck drivers can spread rumors and give false information about bridges being out, ferries closed, and detours lying ahead.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>If you can start damage to a heavily traveled road, passing traffic and the elements will do the rest. Construction gangs can see that too much sand or water is put in concrete or that the road foundation has soft spots. Anyone can scoop ruts in asphalt and macadam roads which turn soft in hot weather; passing trucks will accentuate the ruts to a point where substantial repair will be needed. Dirt roads also can be scooped out. If you are a road laborer, it will be only a few minutes work to divert a small stream from a sluice so that it runs over and eats away the road.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Distribute broken glass, nails, and sharp rocks on roads to puncture tires.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>(b) Passengers</p>

<ol>
  <li>Bus-driver can go past the stop where the enemy wants to get off. Taxi drivers can waste the enemy’s time and make extra money by driving the longest possible route to his destination.</li>
</ol>

<p>(c) Oil and Lubrication</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>See 5 b. (2) (b).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Disconnect the oil pump; this will burn out the main bearings in less than 50 miles of normal driving.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>(d) Radiator</p>

<ol>
  <li>See 5 b. (2) (c).</li>
</ol>

<p>(e) Fuel</p>

<ol>
  <li>See 5 b. (2) (d).</li>
</ol>

<p>(f) Battery and Ignition</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Jam bits of wood into the ignition lock; loosen or exchange connections behind the switchboard; put dirt in spark plugs; damage distributor points.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Turn on the lights in parked cars so that the battery will run down.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Mechanics can ruin batteries in a number of undetectable ways: Take the valve cap off a cell, and drive a screw driver slantwise into the exposed water vent, shattering the plates of the cell; no damage will show when you put the cap back on. Iron or copper filings put into the cells i.e., dropped into the acid, will greatly shorten its life. Copper coins or a few pieces of iron will accomplish the same and more slowly.</p>

    <p>One hundred to 150 cubic centimeters of vinegar in each cell greatly reduces the life of the battery, but the odor of the vinegar may reveal what has happened.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>(g) Gears</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Remove the lubricant from or put too light a lubricant in the transmission and other gears.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>In trucks, tractors, and other machines with heavy gears, fix the gear case insecurely, putting bolts in only half the bolt holes. The gears will be badly jolted in use and will soon need repairs.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>(h) Tires</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Slash or puncture tires of unguarded vehicles. Put a nail inside a match box or other small box, and set it vertically in front of the back tire of a stationary car; when the car starts off, the nail will go neatly through the tire.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>It is easy to damage a tire in a tire repair shop: In fixing flats, spill glass, benzine, caustic soda, or other material inside the casing which will puncture or corrode the tube. If you put a gummy substance inside the tube, the next flat will stick the tube to the casing and make it unusable. Or, when you fix a flat tire, you can simply leave between the tube and the casing the object which caused the flat in the first place.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>In assembling a tire after repair, pump the tube up as fast as you can. Instead of filling out smoothly, it may crease, in which case it will wear out quickly. Or, as you put a tire together, see if you can pinch the tube between the rim of the tire and the rim of the wheel, so that a blow-out will result.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>In putting air into tires, see that they are kept below normal pressure, so that more than an ordinary amount of wear will result. In filling tires on double wheels, inflate the inner tire to a much higher pressure than the outer one; both will wear out more quickly this way. Badly aligned wheels also wear tires out quickly; you can leave wheels out of alignment when they come in for adjustment, or you can spring them out of true with a strong kick, or by driving the car slowly and diagonally into a curb.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>If you have access to stocks of tires, you can rot them by spilling oil, gasoline, caustic acid, or benzine on them. Synthetic rubber, however, is less susceptible to these chemicals.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<h3 id="heading-8-transportation-water">(8) Transportation: Water</h3>

<p>(a) Navigation</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Barge and river boat personnel should spread false rumors about the navigability and conditions of the waterways they travel. Tell other barge and boat captains to follow channels that will take extra time, or cause them to make canal detours.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Barge and river boat captains should navigate with exceeding caution near locks and bridges, to waste their time and to waste the time of other craft which may have to wait on them. If you don’t pump the bilges of ships and barges often enough, they will be slower and harder to navigate. Barges “accidentally” run aground are an efficient time waster too.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Attendants on swing, draw, or bascule bridges can delay traffic over the bridge or in the waterway underneath by being slow. Boat captains can leave unattended draw bridges open in order to hold up road traffic.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Add or subtract compensating magnets to the compass on cargo ships. Demagnetize the compass or maladjust it by concealing a large bar of steel or iron near to it.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>(b) Cargo</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>While loading or unloading, handle cargo carelessly in order to cause damage. Arrange the cargo so that the weakest and lightest crates and boxes will be at the bottom of the hold, while the heaviest ones are on top of them.</p>

    <p>Put hatch covers and tarpaulins on sloppily, so that rain and deck wash will injure the cargo.</p>

    <p>Tie float valves open so that storage tanks will overflow on perishable goods.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<h3 id="heading-9-communications">(9) Communications</h3>

<p>(a) Telephone</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>At office, hotel and exchange switch boards delay putting enemy calls through, give them wrong numbers, cut them off “accidentally,” or forget to disconnect them so that the line cannot be used again.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Hamper official and especially military business by making at least one telephone call a day to an enemy headquarters; when you get them, tell them you have the wrong number.</p>

    <p>Call military or police offices and make anonymous false reports of fires, air raids, bombs.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>In offices and buildings used by the enemy, unscrew the earphone of telephone receivers and remove the diaphragm. Electricians and telephone repair men can make poor connections and damage insulation so that cross talk and other kinds of electrical interference will make conversations hard or impossible to understand.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Put the batteries under automatic switchboards out of commission by dropping nails, metal filings, or coins into the cells. If you can treat half the batteries in this way, the switchboard will stop working. A whole telephone system can be disrupted if you can put 10 percent of the cells in half the batteries of the central battery room out of order.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>(b) Telegraph</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Delay the transmission and delivery of telegrams to enemy destinations.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Garble telegrams to enemy destinations so that another telegram will have to be sent or a long distance call will have to be made. Sometimes it will be possible to do this by changing a single letter in a word — for example, changing “minimum” to “maximum,” so that the person receiving the telegram will not know whether “minimum” or “maximum” is meant.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>(c) Transportation Lines</p>

<ol>
  <li>Cut telephone and telegraph transmission lines. Damage insulation on power lines to cause interference.</li>
</ol>

<p>(d) Mail</p>

<ol>
  <li>Post office employees can see to it that enemy mail is always delayed by one day or more, that it is put in wrong sacks, and so on.</li>
</ol>

<p>(e) Motion Pictures</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Projector operators can ruin newsreels and other enemy propaganda films by bad focusing, speeding up or slowing down the film and by causing frequent breakage in the film.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Audiences can ruin enemy propaganda films by applauding to drown the words of the speaker, by coughing loudly, and by talking.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Anyone can break up a showing of an enemy propaganda film by putting two or three dozen large moths in a paper bag. Take the bag to the movies with you, put it on the floor in an empty section of the theater as you go in and leave it open. The moths will fly out and climb into the projector beam, so that the film will be obscured by fluttering shadows.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>(f) Radio</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Station engineers will find it quite easy to overmodulate transmissions of talks by persons giving enemy propaganda or instructions, so that they will sound as if they were talking through a heavy cotton blanket with a mouth full of marbles.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>In your own apartment building, you can interfere with radio reception at times when the enemy wants everybody to listen. Take an electric light plug off the end of an electric light cord; take some wire out of the cord and tie it across two terminals of a two-prong plug or three terminals of a four-prong plug. Then take it around and put it into as many wall and floor outlets as you can find. Each time you insert the plug into a new circuit, you will blow out a fuse and silence all radios running on power from that circuit until a new fuse is put in.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Damaging insulation on any electrical equipment tends to create radio interference in the immediate neighborhood, particularly on large generators, neon signs, fluorescent lighting, X-ray machines, and power lines. If workmen can damage insulation on a high tension line near an enemy airfield, they will make ground-to-plane radio communications difficult and perhaps impossible during long periods of the day.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<h3 id="heading-10-electric-power">(10) Electric Power</h3>

<p>(a) Turbines, Electric Motors, Transformers</p>

<ol>
  <li>See 5 b. (2) (e), (f),and (g).</li>
</ol>

<p>(b) Transmission Lines</p>

<ol>
  <li>Linesmen can loosen and dirty insulators to cause power leakage. It will be quite easy, too, for them to tie a piece of very heavy string several times back and forth between two parallel transmission lines, winding it several turns around the wire each time. Beforehand, the string should be heavily saturated with salt and then dried. When it rains, the string becomes a conductor, and a short-circuit will result.</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="heading-11-general-interference-with-organizations-and-production">(11) General Interference with Organizations and Production</h3>

<p>(a) Organizations and Conferences</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Insist on doing everything through “channels.” Never permit short-cuts to be taken in order to expedite decisions.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Make “speeches.” Talk as frequently as possible and at great length. Illustrate your “points” by long anecdotes and accounts of personal experiences. Never hesitate to make a few appropriate “patriotic” comments.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>When possible, refer all matters to committees, for “further study and consideration.” Attempt to make the committees as large as possible — never less than five.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Bring up irrelevant issues as frequently as possible.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Haggle over precise wordings of communications, minutes, resolutions.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Refer back to matters decided upon at the last meeting and attempt to re-open the question of the advisability of that decision.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Advocate “caution.” Be “reasonable” and urge your fellow-conferees to be “reasonable” and avoid haste which might result in embarrassments or difficulties later on.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Be worried about the propriety of any decision — raise the question of whether such action as is contemplated lies within the jurisdiction of the group or whether it might conflict with the policy of some higher echelon.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>(b) Managers and Supervisors</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Demand written orders.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>“Misunderstand” orders. Ask endless questions or engage in long correspondence about such orders. Quibble over them when you can.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Do everything possible to delay the delivery of orders. Even though parts of an order may be ready beforehand, don’t deliver it until it is completely ready.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Don’t order new working materials until your current stocks have been virtually exhausted, so that the slightest delay in filling your order will mean a shutdown.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Order high-quality materials which are hard to get. If you don’t get them argue about it. Warn that inferior materials will mean inferior work.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>In making work assignments, always sign out the unimportant jobs first. See that the important jobs are assigned to inefficient workers of poor machines.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Insist on perfect work in relatively unimportant products; send back for refinishing those which have the least flaw. Approve other defective parts whose flaws are not visible to the naked eye.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Make mistakes in routing so that parts and materials will be sent to the wrong place in the plant.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>When training new workers, give incomplete or misleading instructions.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>To lower morale and with it, production, be pleasant to inefficient workers; give them undeserved promotions. Discriminate against efficient workers; complain unjustly about their work.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Hold conferences when there is more critical work to be done.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Multiply paper work in plausible ways.</p>

    <p>Start duplicate files.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Multiply the procedures and clearances involved in issuing instructions, pay checks, and so on. See that three people have to approve everything where one would do.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Apply all regulations to the last letter.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>(c) Office Workers</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Make mistakes in quantities of material when you are copying orders. Confuse similar names. Use wrong addresses.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Prolong correspondence with government bureaus.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Misfile essential documents.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>In making carbon copies, make one too few, so that an extra copying job will have to be done.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Tell important callers the boss is busy or talking on another telephone.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Hold up mail until the next collection.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Spread disturbing rumors that sound like inside dope.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>(d) Employees</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Work slowly. Think out ways to increase the number of movements necessary on your job: use a light hammer instead of a heavy one, try to make a small wrench do when a big one is necessary, use little force where considerable force is needed, and so on.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Contrive as many interruptions to your work as you can: when changing the material on which you are working, as you would on a lathe or punch, take needless time to do it. If you are cutting, shaping or doing other measured work, measure dimensions twice as often as you need to. When you go to the lavatory, spend a longer time there than is necessary.</p>

    <p>Forget tools so that you will have to go back after them.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Even if you understand the language, pretend not to understand instructions in a foreign tongue.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Pretend that instructions are hard to understand, and ask to have them repeated more than once. Or pretend that you are particularly anxious to do your work, and pester the foreman with unnecessary questions.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Do your work poorly and blame it on bad tools, machinery, or equipment. Complain that these things are preventing you from doing your job right.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Never pass on your skill and experience to a new or less skillful worker.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Snarl up administration in every possible way. Fill out forms illegibly so that they will have to be done over; make mistakes or omit requested information in forms.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>If possible, join or help organize a group for presenting employee problems to the management. See that the procedures adopted are as inconvenient as possible for the management, involving the presence of a large number of employees at each presentation, entailing more than one meeting for each grievance, bringing up problems which are largely imaginary, and so on.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Misroute materials.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Mix good parts with unusable scrap and rejected parts.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<h3 id="heading-12-general-devices-for-lowering-morale-and-creating-confusion">(12) General Devices for Lowering Morale and Creating Confusion</h3>

<p>(a) Give lengthy and incomprehensible explanations when questioned.</p>

<p>(b) Report imaginary spies or danger to the Gestapo or police.</p>

<p>(c) Act stupid.</p>

<p>(d) Be as irritable and quarrelsome as possible without getting yourself into trouble.</p>

<p>(e) Misunderstand all sorts of regulations concerning such matters as rationing, transportation, traffic regulations.</p>

<p>(f) Complain against ersatz materials.</p>

<p>(g) In public treat axis nationals or quislings coldly.</p>

<p>(h) Stop all conversation when axis nationals or quislings enter a cafe.</p>

<p>(i) Cry and sob hysterically at every occasion, especially when confronted by government clerks.</p>

<p>(j) Boycott all movies, entertainments, concerts, newspapers which are in any way connected with the quisling authorities.</p>

<p>(k) Do not cooperate in salvage schemes.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Simple Sabotage Field Manual was a collection of simple sabotage techniques gathered by the Office of Strategic Services (predecessor of the CIA) during World War II to be distributed among workers in enemy countries and disrupt their industry and military.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://lamaquinadeturing.su/simplesabotage.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://lamaquinadeturing.su/simplesabotage.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">The case for a better web</title><link href="https://lamaquinadeturing.su/en/2024/08/the-case-for-a-better-web/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The case for a better web" /><published>2024-08-20T14:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-20T14:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://lamaquinadeturing.su/en/2024/08/the-case-for-a-better-web</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lamaquinadeturing.su/en/2024/08/the-case-for-a-better-web/"><![CDATA[<p>There is a growing discontent around the current state of the World Wide Web.</p>

<p>Web 1.0 felt like a place of freedom and creativity. Maybe I’m being romantic, for sure had to have its issues… But remember the whimsical sites in Geocities, the simplicity of email discussion lists or the anonymity of IRC?</p>

<p>That air of innocence has vanished. For good. A few decades later it has become a dystopian trap of surveillance and censorship, where governments and platforms gorge on our attention and personal data and force-feed us ads and fake news. The web today, as most people experience it, is a horrible place.</p>

<p>This has been discussed for a while, but 2024 has seen a peak of discussions and contributions to this topic. I suggest three converging causes to this renaissance of the web: the late stage of <a href="https://pluralistic.net/2023/01/08/watch-the-surpluses/" class="link-external">enshittification</a> of the platforms; the revival of the personal blogs (and podcasts) during the covid pandemic; and the nostalgia of the generations that enjoyed the old web as teenagers and are now in their 30s and 40s.</p>

<p>This is an on-going collection of essays, articles, projects and manifestos about what went wrong and what to do to make it right.</p>

<h2 id="heading-the-disenshittified-internet-starts-with-loyal-user-agents"><a href="https://pluralistic.net/2024/05/07/treacherous-computing/" class="link-external">The disenshittified internet starts with loyal “user agents”</a></h2>

<p>By <a href="https://mamot.fr/@pluralistic" class="link-mastodon">Cory Doctorow</a>, 7 May, 2024.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>A web browser that’s a “user agent” is a comforting thought. An agent’s job is to serve you and your interests. […] A “faithless” user agent is utterly different from a “clumsy” user agent, and faithless user agents have become the norm. Indeed, as crude early internet clients progressed in sophistication, they grew increasingly treacherous. Most non-browser tools are designed for treachery.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="heading-reweirding-the-web"><a href="https://webdirections.org/blog/reweirding-the-web/" class="link-external">Reweirding the Web</a></h2>

<p>By <a href="https://indieweb.social/@johnallsopp" class="link-mastodon">John Allsopp</a>, 3 May, 2024.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>More than at any time in the last decade or so I feel there’s a desire for this more personal web, and the tools and ideas to make it happen. So reclaim your little plot of the web, make it a bit weirder, a bit better. And connect with others who are doing likewise. It’s what drew me to the Web 30 years ago. One of the best decisions I ever made.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>See also the <a href="https://deshittify.us/" class="link-external">The Disenshittify Project</a>, 30 April, 2024.</p>

<h2 id="heading-we-can-have-a-different-web"><a href="https://www.citationneeded.news/we-can-have-a-different-web/" class="link-external">We can have a different web</a></h2>

<p>By <a href="https://hachyderm.io/@molly0xfff" class="link-mastodon">Molly White</a>, 1 May, 2024.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Many yearn for the “good old days” of the web. We could have those good old days back — or something even better — and if anything, it would be easier now than it ever was.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="heading-we-need-to-rewild-the-internet"><a href="https://www.noemamag.com/we-need-to-rewild-the-internet/" class="link-external">We Need To Rewild The Internet</a></h2>

<p>By <a href="https://hachyderm.io/@mariafarrell@mastodon.social" class="link-mastodon">Maria Farrel</a> and <a href="https://hachyderm.io/@robin@mastodon.social" class="link-mastodon">Robin Berjon</a>, 16 April, 2024.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Ecologists have reoriented their field as a “crisis discipline,” a field of study that’s not just about learning things but about saving them. We technologists need to do the same. Rewilding the internet connects and grows what people are doing across regulation, standards-setting and new ways of organizing and building infrastructure, to tell a shared story of where we want to go. It’s a shared vision with many strategies. The instruments we need to shift away from extractive technological monocultures are at hand or ready to be built.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="heading-a-manifesto-for-small-static-web-apps"><a href="https://rosswintle.uk/2024/02/a-manifesto-for-small-static-web-apps/" class="link-external">A manifesto for small, static, web apps</a></h2>

<p>By <a href="https://fosstodon.org/@ross" class="link-mastodon">Ross Wintle</a>, 17 February, 2024.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Static first/only, No login, Don’t store user data, Use the smallest JS library possible, Use web standards as much as possible, Use simple build steps that won’t break, “Done” is a goal, Zero-maintenance (and easy maintenance) is a goal, Don’t minify, Be accessible.</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Web" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[There is a growing discontent around the current state of the World Wide Web.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://lamaquinadeturing.su/ocean.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://lamaquinadeturing.su/ocean.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry xml:lang="ca"><title type="html">Aquest lloc web no utilitza galetes</title><link href="https://lamaquinadeturing.su/ca/2024/08/aquest-lloc-web-no-utilitza-galetes/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Aquest lloc web no utilitza galetes" /><published>2024-08-14T17:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-14T17:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://lamaquinadeturing.su/ca/2024/08/aquest-lloc-web-no-utilitza-galetes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lamaquinadeturing.su/ca/2024/08/aquest-lloc-web-no-utilitza-galetes/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Aquest lloc web no utilitza galetes.</strong></p>

<p>No recull les teves dades per millorar la teva experiència de navegació, ni serveix anuncis personalitzats ni analitza el teu trànsit.</p>

<p>No has de consentir a res per a una experiència de navegació òptima.</p>

<p>No has de configurar la teva configuració de privacitat a través d’una llista de centenars de socis.</p>

<p><strong>Aquest lloc web no sap si estàs utilitzant un bloquejador d’anuncis.</strong></p>

<p>Aquest lloc web no depèn de la publicitat, per tant, no desactivis el bloqueig d’anuncis. Si en tens un, no dubtis a habilitar-lo.</p>

<p>Si no tens un bloquejador d’anuncis, et recomano que n’instal·lis un. Si el teu navegador no ho admet, considera canviar a un navegador diferent.</p>

<p><strong>Aquest lloc web no té una versió sense anuncis de pagament.</strong></p>

<p>No has de triar entre una subscripció de pagament o consentir que centenars d’intermediaris de dades rastregin i venguin les teves dades personals.</p>

<p>Altres llocs web requereixen una subscripció per accedir al seu contingut, la qual cosa està bé. Però això és diferent del model de “pagar o consentir”.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Web" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Aquest lloc web no utilitza galetes.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://lamaquinadeturing.su/questioning-moon.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://lamaquinadeturing.su/questioning-moon.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">This website does not use cookies</title><link href="https://lamaquinadeturing.su/en/2024/08/this-website-does-not-use-cookies/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="This website does not use cookies" /><published>2024-08-14T17:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-14T17:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://lamaquinadeturing.su/en/2024/08/this-website-does-not-use-cookies</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lamaquinadeturing.su/en/2024/08/this-website-does-not-use-cookies/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>This website does not use cookies.</strong></p>

<p>It does not collect your data to enhance your browsing experience, nor serve personalized ads or analyze your traffic.</p>

<p>You do not have to consent to anything for an optimal browsing experience.</p>

<p>You do not have to configure your privacy settings over a list of hundreds of partners.</p>

<p><strong>This website does not know if you are using an ad blocker.</strong></p>

<p>This website does not rely on advertising, so please do not disable your ad blocker. If you have it, feel free to enable it.</p>

<p>If you do not have an ad blocker, I recommend you to install one. If your browser does not support it, consider switching to a different browser.</p>

<p><strong>This website does not have a paid ad-free version.</strong></p>

<p>You do not have to choose between a paid subscription or consenting to hundreds of data brokers tracking and selling your personal data.</p>

<p>Some other websites require a subscription to access their content, which is fine. But that is different than the “pay or consent” model.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Web" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This website does not use cookies.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://lamaquinadeturing.su/questioning-moon.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://lamaquinadeturing.su/questioning-moon.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry xml:lang="es"><title type="html">Esta web no utiliza cookies</title><link href="https://lamaquinadeturing.su/es/2024/08/esta-web-no-utiliza-cookies/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Esta web no utiliza cookies" /><published>2024-08-14T17:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-14T17:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://lamaquinadeturing.su/es/2024/08/esta-web-no-utiliza-cookies</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lamaquinadeturing.su/es/2024/08/esta-web-no-utiliza-cookies/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Este sitio web no utiliza cookies.</strong></p>

<p>No recoge tus datos para mejorar su experiencia de navegación, ni sirve anuncios personalizados ni analiza tu tráfico.</p>

<p>No tienes que consentir a nada para una experiencia de navegación óptima.</p>

<p>No tienes que configurar tus opciones de privacidad a través de una lista de centenares de socios.</p>

<p><strong>Este sitio web no sabe si estás utilizando un bloqueador de anuncios.</strong></p>

<p>Este sitio web no depende de la publicidad, por lo tanto, no desactives el bloqueo de anuncios. Si lo tienes, no dudes en habilitarlo.</p>

<p>Si no tienes un bloqueador de anuncios, te recomiendo que instales uno. Si tu navegador no lo admite, considera cambiar a un navegador diferente.</p>

<p><strong>Este sitio web no tiene una versión sin anuncios de pago.</strong></p>

<p>No tienes que elegir entre una suscripción de pago o consentir que centenares de intermediarios de datos rastreen y vendan tus datos personales.</p>

<p>Otros sitios web requieren una suscripción para acceder a su contenido, lo cual está bien. Pero esto es diferente al modelo de “pagar o consentir”.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Web" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Este sitio web no utiliza cookies.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://lamaquinadeturing.su/questioning-moon.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://lamaquinadeturing.su/questioning-moon.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Implementing the search function in a static web site</title><link href="https://lamaquinadeturing.su/en/2024/08/implementing-search-function-in-static-web-site/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Implementing the search function in a static web site" /><published>2024-08-09T11:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-09T11:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://lamaquinadeturing.su/en/2024/08/implementing-search-function-in-static-web-site</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lamaquinadeturing.su/en/2024/08/implementing-search-function-in-static-web-site/"><![CDATA[<p>Static web sites <a href="/en/2024/08/the-case-for-a-better-web/">are the best</a>. They are fast, lightweight, safe and content-centric. However, not having a server comes with its sacrifices. I can go without forms, user accounts or comments, but the thing I miss the most is <em>searching</em>.</p>

<h2 id="heading-the-poor-mans-search-function">The poor man’s search function</h2>

<p>Usually, the alternative has been the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">site:</code> operator in Google: a form in your website would transform the search string into a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">site:</code> query and redirect it to Google. Purists can do the same with <a href="https://duckduckgo.com/duckduckgo-help-pages/results/syntax/" class="link-external">DuckDuckGo</a>. But that leaves me relying on notoriously unreliable companies, which can drop this feature at any moment or hide it behind a pawyall.</p>

<p>And I wondered: is there a way to have my own search function?</p>

<h2 id="heading-is-static-search-even-possible">Is static search even possible?</h2>

<p>My wishlist for a search function was:</p>
<ol>
  <li>Doesn’t depend on an external API.</li>
  <li>Has to be lightweight, ie. downloading all the posts and searching them is not an option.</li>
  <li>Has to be reasonably good at finding results, but not perfect. For instance, I can do without full-text search.</li>
</ol>

<p>With that in mind, I started designing my own static search function. The basic idea was to generate some kind of index that would allow for static searches using Javascript.</p>

<p>There are some nice Javascript libraries that will consume texts and provide a search function, like <a href="https://lunrjs.com" class="link-external">Lunr</a>. It even lets you <a href="https://lunrjs.com/guides/index_prebuilding.html" class="link-external">pre-build the serch index</a>, so it can be downloaded as a static JSON file. As a test, I created a Lunr JSON index with <a href="/es/2020/04/cibernetica-en-el-breve-diccionario-filosofico-1954/">the</a> <a href="/es/2020/05/cibernetica-al-servicio-del-comunismo/">three</a> <a href="/es/2020/05/cuando-la-inteligencia-artificial-desplazo-la-cibernetica/">posts</a> in Spanish in the blog, as they are the longest right now. The result is the following:</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Posts</th>
      <th>Rendered Post Size<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>
</th>
      <th>Lunr JSON Index Size</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="/es/2020/04/cibernetica-en-el-breve-diccionario-filosofico-1954/">Post 1</a></td>
      <td>2.72 KB</td>
      <td>12.39 KB</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="/es/2020/05/cibernetica-al-servicio-del-comunismo/">Post 2</a></td>
      <td>87.16 KB</td>
      <td>141.89 KB</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="/es/2020/05/cuando-la-inteligencia-artificial-desplazo-la-cibernetica/">Post 3</a></td>
      <td>3.27 KB</td>
      <td>15.04 KB</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>All three posts</td>
      <td>93.16 KB</td>
      <td>158.32 KB</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>As it can be seen, the Lunr index grows linearly to the size of the text, but also it becomes larger than the text itself! At least for this small amount of content, it would be better to just download the text of the posts.</p>

<p>Maybe Lunr was too fancy for me, so I should implement my own search library.</p>

<h2 id="heading-putting-it-down-in-words">Putting it down in words</h2>

<p>The basic functionality of a search function is to map a query to posts that contain them. So a very initial implementation would be to collect all the words from all the posts and map each one to a list of posts. Then, when the user enters a query, the words of such query can be found in the search index.</p>

<p>As this site uses Jekyll, the static generation of the index would be in Ruby, while the search of the index would be in Javascript. Let’s focus on the former.</p>

<p>I’ll show some snippets of code, but they are greatly simplified and are not expected to actually run:</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-ruby" data-lang="ruby"><span class="n">index</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">{}</span>
<span class="n">site</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">posts</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">docs</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">each</span> <span class="k">do</span> <span class="o">|</span><span class="n">post</span><span class="o">|</span>
    <span class="n">rendered_content</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">site</span>
        <span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">liquid_renderer</span>
        <span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">file</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">post</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">path</span><span class="p">)</span>
        <span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">parse</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">post</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">content</span><span class="p">)</span>
        <span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">render</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">site</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">site_payload</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="n">html_content</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">site</span>
        <span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">find_converter_instance</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="no">Jekyll</span><span class="o">::</span><span class="no">Converters</span><span class="o">::</span><span class="no">Markdown</span><span class="p">)</span>
        <span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">convert</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">rendered_content</span><span class="p">)</span>

    <span class="n">text_content</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">html_content</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">gsub</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sr">/&lt;\/?[^&gt;]*&gt;/</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s1">' '</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="o">...</span></code></pre></figure>

<p>In this iterator, the posts of the site are programmatically rendered using the Liquid parser and the Markdown converter to HTML. The result is the HTML as it would be displayed by the web browser. Then, the HTML tags are stripped, so what remains is the pure text content.</p>

<p>Let’s get the words:</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-ruby" data-lang="ruby">    <span class="o">...</span>
    <span class="n">lang</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">post</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">data</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="s1">'lang'</span><span class="p">]</span>
    <span class="n">valid_chars</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="s1">'a-zA-Z0-9áéíóúàèìòùäëïöüâêîôûçñÁÉÍÓÚÀÈÌÒÙÄËÏÖÜÂÊÎÔÛÇÑ·'</span>

    <span class="n">text_content</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">text_content</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">gsub</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sr">/[^</span><span class="si">#{</span><span class="n">valid_chars</span><span class="si">}</span><span class="sr">]/</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s1">' '</span><span class="p">)</span>

    <span class="n">words</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">text_content</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">downcase</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">split</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sr">/\s+/</span><span class="p">)</span>
        <span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">filter</span> <span class="p">{</span> <span class="o">|</span><span class="n">word</span><span class="o">|</span> <span class="n">word</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">length</span> <span class="o">&gt;</span> <span class="mi">1</span> <span class="p">}</span>
        <span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">filter</span> <span class="p">{</span> <span class="o">|</span><span class="n">word</span><span class="o">|</span> <span class="o">!</span><span class="n">word</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">match?</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sr">/^\d+$/</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">}</span>
        <span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">filter</span> <span class="p">{</span> <span class="o">|</span><span class="n">word</span><span class="o">|</span> <span class="o">!</span><span class="n">stopwords</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">lang</span><span class="p">].</span><span class="nf">include?</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">word</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">}</span>
        <span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">sort</span>
        <span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">uniq</span>
    <span class="o">...</span></code></pre></figure>

<p>Here the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">text_content</code> string is filtered, excluding anything that is not a valid character in one of the languages of the blog. This means that punctuation marks or other symbols are removed.</p>

<p>Then, the resulting string is split by words, excluding short ones or numbers. A list of stopwords for the language of the post is used to remove common words, like “then” or “one”. There are projects that maintain lists of stopwords, like <a href="https://github.com/nltk/nltk_data/blob/gh-pages/packages/corpora/stopwords.zip" class="link-external">NLTK</a>.</p>

<p>Finally, the words are sorted and duplicates are removed. Great! This is the list of unique words from one post, after removing garbage like stopwords, short words or numbers. Let’s add them to the index:</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-ruby" data-lang="ruby">    <span class="o">...</span>
    <span class="n">words</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">each</span> <span class="k">do</span> <span class="o">|</span><span class="n">word</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">count</span><span class="o">|</span>
        <span class="n">index</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">lang</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="o">||=</span> <span class="p">{}</span>
        <span class="n">index</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">lang</span><span class="p">][</span><span class="n">word</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="o">||=</span> <span class="p">[]</span>
        <span class="n">index</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">lang</span><span class="p">][</span><span class="n">word</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="o">&lt;&lt;</span> <span class="n">post_index</span>
    <span class="k">end</span>
<span class="k">end</span></code></pre></figure>

<p>Note that per each word in a given language, it maps to a list of posts referenced by an “index”. This index is the position in the array of posts at the end of the index structure.</p>

<p>Let’s use an example. The following snippet is taken from the Markdown source of this <a href="/en/2024/07/cybernetics-in-a-Dictionary-of-philosophy-1967/">post</a>:</p>

<p><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">**Cybernetics**[^1], the science of the common features of processes and control systems in technological devices, living organisms and human organisations. The principles of C. were first set forth by Wiener (q.v.)</code></p>

<p>After rendering it:</p>

<p><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cybernetics&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, the science of the common features of processes and control systems in technological devices, living organisms and human organisations. The principles of C. were first set forth by Wiener (q.v.).&lt;p&gt;</code></p>

<p>After removing the HTML tags:</p>

<p><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Cybernetics 1, the science of the common features of processes and control systems in technological devices, living organisms and human organisations. The principles of C. were first set forth by Wiener (q.v.).</code></p>

<p>Removing the invalid characters:</p>

<p><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Cybernetics 1 the science of the common features of processes and control systems in technological devices living organisms and human organisations The principles of C were first set forth by Wiener q v</code></p>

<p>And after filtering out short words, numbers and stopwords:</p>

<p><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Cybernetics science common features processes control systems technological devices living organisms human organisations principles set forth Wiener</code></p>

<p>Last step, sorting and removing repeated words:</p>

<p><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">common control cybernetics devices features forth human living organisations organisms principles processes science set systems technological wiener</code></p>

<p>From this, the index would look as follows:</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-json" data-lang="json"><span class="p">{</span><span class="w">
    </span><span class="nl">"index"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">{</span><span class="w">
        </span><span class="nl">"en"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">{</span><span class="w">
            </span><span class="nl">"common"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">[</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">],</span><span class="w">
            </span><span class="nl">"control"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">[</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">],</span><span class="w">
            </span><span class="nl">"cybernetics"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">[</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">],</span><span class="w">
            </span><span class="nl">"devices"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">[</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">],</span><span class="w">
            </span><span class="nl">"features"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">[</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">],</span><span class="w">
            </span><span class="nl">"forth"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">[</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">],</span><span class="w">
            </span><span class="nl">"human"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">[</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">],</span><span class="w">
            </span><span class="nl">"living"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">[</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">],</span><span class="w">
            </span><span class="nl">"organisations"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">[</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">],</span><span class="w">
            </span><span class="nl">"organisms"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">[</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">],</span><span class="w">
            </span><span class="nl">"principles"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">[</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">],</span><span class="w">
            </span><span class="nl">"processes"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">[</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">],</span><span class="w">
            </span><span class="nl">"science"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">[</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">],</span><span class="w">
            </span><span class="nl">"set"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">[</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">],</span><span class="w">
            </span><span class="nl">"systems"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">[</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">],</span><span class="w">
            </span><span class="nl">"technological"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">[</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">],</span><span class="w">
            </span><span class="nl">"wiener"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">[</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">],</span><span class="w">
        </span><span class="p">}</span><span class="w">
    </span><span class="p">},</span><span class="w">
    </span><span class="nl">"posts"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">[</span><span class="w">
        </span><span class="p">{</span><span class="w">
            </span><span class="nl">"url"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"/en/2024/07/cybernetics-in-a-Dictionary-of-philosophy-1967/"</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w">
            </span><span class="nl">"title"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"“Cybernetics” (in A Dictionary of Philosophy, 1967)"</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w">
            </span><span class="nl">"date"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"2024-07-27 19:00:00 +0200"</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w">
            </span><span class="nl">"lang"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"en"</span><span class="w">
        </span><span class="p">}</span><span class="w">
    </span><span class="p">]</span><span class="w">
</span><span class="p">}</span></code></pre></figure>

<p>The current JSON search index in this format for the 7 posts in 3 languages of the site is 52 KB. Not bad compared to the 141 KB of Lunr for just 3 posts. All in all, 50 KB or 140 KB may be are not very important nowadays, as some images in this site are larger than that. But I’d like this blog to grow enough so the size of the index matters.</p>

<h2 id="heading-wait-doesnt-that-look-like-a-bloom-filter">Wait, doesn’t that look like a Bloom filter?</h2>

<p>Indeed, why not use a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bloom_filter" class="link-wikipedia">Bloom filter</a>, instead of a map of words? After all, a Bloom filter is super compact: 1 bit per word!</p>

<p>The issue is that a Bloom filter only tells you if a given entry is (probably) part of a set. In other words, it maps a given key to a <em>boolean value.</em> But in my case each key must map to a <em>list of values,</em> the posts that contain that word.</p>

<p>There are two alternatives. One is to implement a Bloom filter per post. But that would be prohibitive as the number of posts grows. The other is to implement a modified Bloom filter that can store <em>values.</em></p>

<p>Some kind of <em>Bloom map.</em></p>

<p>Each entry in the Bloom table would be a set, containing the values that were assigned by the hash functions. Then, the test operation would return the subset of values present in all the entries mapped by the key, if any.</p>

<p>As far as I know, no such hybrid between a Bloom filter and a hash table exists. Maybe for a reason? I am not 100% sure if this would really preserve the accuracy of a Bloom filter, but I made a quick implementation. The result is that even using very compact encodings of this Bloom map (I’m talking about base 36 indices for sparse tables) it still would be less efficient than the previous approach that just stores the list of words. In particular, the Bloom maps would need 82 KB, compared to the 52 KB of the word map.</p>

<p>I’ll leave that implementation in a branch. Maybe, in the long run, it outperforms the word map.</p>

<h2 id="heading-levenshtein-and-his-friends-burkhard-and-keller">Levenshtein and his friends Burkhard and Keller</h2>

<p>Now that the search index is generated, it’s time to do some searching in the web browser.</p>

<p>The search index contains (almost) all the words of the posts. A trivial approach would be to take the search query word by word and try to match it against the index. Every time there is a match, one point is given to the matched posts. If the query has 4 words, then the maximum score would be 4. The matching posts are displayed sorted by their score.</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-javascript" data-lang="javascript"><span class="kd">function</span> <span class="nf">search</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">query</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">word_map</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
  <span class="kd">const</span> <span class="nx">query_words</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">[...</span> <span class="k">new</span> <span class="nc">Set</span><span class="p">(</span>
    <span class="nf">to_ansi</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">query</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">toLowerCase</span><span class="p">()</span>
    <span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">split</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sr">/</span><span class="se">\s</span><span class="sr">+/</span><span class="p">)</span>
  <span class="p">)];</span>
  <span class="kd">let</span> <span class="nx">results</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="k">new</span> <span class="nb">Map</span><span class="p">;</span>
  <span class="nx">index</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">forEach</span><span class="p">((</span><span class="nx">lang</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">word_map</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">=&gt;</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="nx">query_words</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">forEach</span><span class="p">((</span><span class="nx">query_word</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">=&gt;</span> <span class="p">{</span>
      <span class="kd">const</span> <span class="nx">posts</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nx">word_map</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">get</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">query_word</span><span class="p">);</span>
      <span class="k">if </span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">posts</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
        <span class="nx">posts</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">forEach</span><span class="p">((</span><span class="nx">post_index</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">=&gt;</span> <span class="p">{</span>
          <span class="kd">let</span> <span class="nx">score</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nx">results</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">get</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">post_index</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">||</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">;</span>
          <span class="nx">results</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">set</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">post_index</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">score</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">);</span>
        <span class="p">});</span>
      <span class="p">}</span>
    <span class="p">});</span>
  <span class="p">});</span>
  <span class="k">return</span> <span class="nx">results</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="p">}</span></code></pre></figure>

<p>That will be the base search algorithm, but I would like it to be slightly smarter than that. After all, we are all used to fancy search engines that will find similar words, or match just prefixes. Instead of doing an exact match of the words in the index, the search could find <em>similar</em> words. An obvious optimization is to ignore accents. But how to match other similarities? For instance, “cybernetics” is very similar to “cibernètica” (Catalan).</p>

<p>Enter Levenshtein.</p>

<p>The <em>similarity</em> between two words could be defined as the <em>distance</em> between these words. This is what the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Levenshtein_distance" class="link-wikipedia">Levenshtein distance</a> function does: it calculates how far away two words are. The distance is defined as how many letters need to be added, removed or substituted to go from one word to the other. In the case of “cybernetics”, it needs 2 substitutions to become “cibernètica”, if we ignore the accents.</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-javascript" data-lang="javascript"><span class="kd">function</span> <span class="nf">search</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">query</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">word_map</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
  <span class="kd">const</span> <span class="nx">query_words</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">[...</span> <span class="k">new</span> <span class="nc">Set</span><span class="p">(</span>
    <span class="nf">to_ansi</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">query</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">toLowerCase</span><span class="p">()</span>
    <span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">split</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sr">/</span><span class="se">\s</span><span class="sr">+/</span><span class="p">)</span>
  <span class="p">)];</span>
  <span class="kd">let</span> <span class="nx">results</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="k">new</span> <span class="nb">Map</span><span class="p">;</span>
  <span class="nx">index</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">forEach</span><span class="p">((</span><span class="nx">lang</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">word_map</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">=&gt;</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="nx">query_words</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">forEach</span><span class="p">((</span><span class="nx">query_word</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">=&gt;</span> <span class="p">{</span>
      <span class="kd">const</span> <span class="nx">max_distance</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nb">Math</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">max</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nb">Math</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">floor</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">query_word</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">length</span> <span class="o">/</span> <span class="mi">3</span><span class="p">),</span> <span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">);</span>
      <span class="nx">word_map</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">forEach</span><span class="p">((</span><span class="nx">posts</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">index_word</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">=&gt;</span> <span class="p">{</span>
        <span class="kd">const</span> <span class="nx">distance</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nf">levenshtein_distance</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">query_word</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">index_word</span><span class="p">);</span>
        <span class="k">if </span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">distance</span> <span class="o">&lt;=</span> <span class="nx">max_distance</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
          <span class="nx">posts</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">forEach</span><span class="p">((</span><span class="nx">post_index</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">=&gt;</span> <span class="p">{</span>
              <span class="kd">const</span> <span class="nx">score</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">1</span> <span class="o">-</span> <span class="nx">distance</span> <span class="o">/</span> <span class="nb">Math</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">max</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">query_word</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">length</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">index_word</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">length</span><span class="p">);</span>
              <span class="nx">results</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">set</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">post_index</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">results</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">get</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">post_index</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">||</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="nx">score</span><span class="p">);</span>
          <span class="p">});</span>
        <span class="p">}</span>
      <span class="p">});</span>
    <span class="p">});</span>
  <span class="p">});</span>
  <span class="k">return</span> <span class="nx">results</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="p">}</span></code></pre></figure>

<p>Good, we now have a precise definition of similarity. So the search algorithm can match not only exact words from the index, but also similar words whose Levenshtein distance is below a certain threshold (in particular, the maximum distance allowed is 1/3 of the length of the word, in other words, two words should share 2/3 of their letters to be considered similar).</p>

<p>Also, now the score is not 1 per each match, because matches may be similar but not exact. How exact? The normalized distance between the words, meaning a distance of 1 in a 5-letter word is an 80% similarity.</p>

<p>But there is another difference between this code and the previous one: before it was using a map to find exact matches, which is fast, while now it is comparing each word from the query to each word from the index. It has gone from O(1) to O(n<sup>2</sup>)!<sup id="fnref:2" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote">2</a></sup></p>

<p>Let’s bring some friends of Levenshtein to the party. In particular, Burkhard and Keller and their tree structure, the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BK-tree" class="link-wikipedia">BK-Tree</a>. A BK-Tree is a data structure that can organize values based on their relative distance, and allows to quickly navigate it to find the values with a similarity below the given threshold.</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-javascript" data-lang="javascript"><span class="kd">function</span> <span class="nf">build_forest</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">word_map</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
  <span class="kd">let</span> <span class="nx">forest</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="k">new</span> <span class="nb">Map</span><span class="p">;</span>
  <span class="nx">index</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">forEach</span><span class="p">((</span><span class="nx">lang</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">word_map</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">=&gt;</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="kd">let</span> <span class="nx">tree</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="k">new</span> <span class="nc">BKTree</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">levenshtein_distance</span><span class="p">);</span>
    <span class="nx">word_map</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">forEach</span><span class="p">((</span><span class="nx">posts</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">index_word</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">=&gt;</span> <span class="p">{</span>
      <span class="nx">tree</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">add</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">index_word</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">posts</span><span class="p">);</span>
    <span class="p">});</span>
    <span class="nx">forest</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">set</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">lang</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">tree</span><span class="p">);</span>
  <span class="p">});</span>
  <span class="k">return</span> <span class="nx">forest</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="p">}</span>

<span class="kd">function</span> <span class="nf">search</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">query</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">word_map</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
  <span class="kd">const</span> <span class="nx">query_words</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">[...</span> <span class="k">new</span> <span class="nc">Set</span><span class="p">(</span>
    <span class="nf">to_ansi</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">query</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">toLowerCase</span><span class="p">()</span>
    <span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">split</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sr">/</span><span class="se">\s</span><span class="sr">+/</span><span class="p">)</span>
  <span class="p">)];</span>

  <span class="kd">let</span> <span class="nx">forest</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nf">build_forest</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">word_map</span><span class="p">);</span>
  <span class="kd">let</span> <span class="nx">results</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="k">new</span> <span class="nb">Map</span><span class="p">;</span>

  <span class="nx">forest</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">forEach</span><span class="p">((</span><span class="nx">tree</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">=&gt;</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="nx">query_words</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">forEach</span><span class="p">((</span><span class="nx">query_word</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">=&gt;</span> <span class="p">{</span>
      <span class="kd">const</span> <span class="nx">max_distance</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nb">Math</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">max</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nb">Math</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">floor</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">query_word</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">length</span> <span class="o">/</span> <span class="mi">3</span><span class="p">),</span> <span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">);</span>
      <span class="nx">tree</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">search</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">query_word</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">max_distance</span><span class="p">).</span><span class="nf">forEach</span><span class="p">((</span><span class="nx">search_result</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">=&gt;</span> <span class="p">{</span>
        <span class="nx">search_result</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">value</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">forEach</span><span class="p">((</span><span class="nx">post_index</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">=&gt;</span> <span class="p">{</span>
          <span class="kd">const</span> <span class="nx">score</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nx">search_result</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">score</span><span class="p">;</span>
          <span class="nx">results</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">set</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">post_index</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">results</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">get</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">post_index</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">||</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="nx">score</span><span class="p">);</span>
        <span class="p">});</span>
      <span class="p">});</span>
    <span class="p">});</span>
  <span class="p">});</span>
  <span class="k">return</span> <span class="nx">results</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="p">}</span></code></pre></figure>

<p>In this new code, a BK-Tree is constructed for each word index, and now these trees can be used to search for similar words below a certain threshold with a time complexity of O(log n). That’s more like it.</p>

<h2 id="heading-looking-for-the-headline">Looking for the headline</h2>

<p>The fuzzy search function that was implemented above will match similar words. But surely the user, after typing “cyber”, will expect <a href="/en/2024/07/cybernetics-in-a-Dictionary-of-philosophy-1967/">“Cybernetics” (in A Dictionary of Philosophy, 1967)</a> to appear in the results.</p>

<p>Implementing a prefix match for all the words is possible, for instance with a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Radix_tree" class="link-wikipedia">radix tree</a> structure. But that would probably generate too many results, many of them unuseful. If the user types “app”, do they want results about applications but also about apples?</p>

<p>Still, what is overkill for the content can be adequate if limited to the title. In addition to the score provided by the fuzzy search with the word map, I also added a substring search:</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-javascript" data-lang="javascript"><span class="kd">function</span> <span class="nf">search_titles</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">query</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">post_list</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
  <span class="kd">const</span> <span class="nx">query_words</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">[...</span> <span class="k">new</span> <span class="nc">Set</span><span class="p">(</span>
    <span class="nf">to_ansi</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">query</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">toLowerCase</span><span class="p">()</span>
    <span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">split</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sr">/</span><span class="se">\s</span><span class="sr">+/</span><span class="p">)</span>
  <span class="p">)];</span>

  <span class="kd">let</span> <span class="nx">results</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="k">new</span> <span class="nb">Map</span><span class="p">;</span>
  <span class="k">for </span><span class="p">(</span><span class="kd">let</span> <span class="nx">i</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">;</span> <span class="nx">i</span> <span class="o">&lt;</span> <span class="nx">post_list</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">length</span><span class="p">;</span> <span class="nx">i</span><span class="o">++</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="kd">let</span> <span class="nx">title</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nx">post_list</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="nx">i</span><span class="p">].</span><span class="nx">title</span><span class="p">;</span>
    <span class="kd">let</span> <span class="nx">score</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">;</span>
    <span class="nx">query_words</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">forEach</span><span class="p">((</span><span class="nx">query_word</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">=&gt;</span> <span class="p">{</span>
      <span class="k">if </span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">title</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">includes</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">word</span><span class="p">))</span> <span class="p">{</span>
        <span class="nx">score</span> <span class="o">+=</span> <span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">;</span>
      <span class="p">}</span>
    <span class="p">});</span>

    <span class="k">if </span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">score</span> <span class="o">&gt;</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
      <span class="nx">results</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">set</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">i</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">score</span><span class="p">);</span>
    <span class="p">}</span>
  <span class="p">}</span>
  <span class="k">return</span> <span class="nx">results</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="p">}</span></code></pre></figure>

<p>The previous code takes the words of the search query and checks if they are a substring of a post title. For each word that is a substring of a title, that post gets 1 point. The score of the title search is added to the score of the fuzzy search, and that is how posts are displayed in the search box and how they are sorted.</p>

<h2 id="heading-conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>I am quite satisfied with the static search function I implemented for this website. It is quite lightweight: 52 KB, compared to the 141 KB of Lunr or the 82 KB of a <em>Bloom map.</em> Still, the search experience feels similar to what can be expected from a full text search. Go ahead and test it yourself.</p>

<p>Obviously, searching web pages is complicated, after all Google was built around this. If I type for “levens” I want the search function to return me results for Levenshtein, but that will not happen as it is too dissimilar (45% similarity). And yet, it will match “leaves” and “even” (66% similarity).</p>

<p>As the blog grows, maybe I will have to revisit the implementation in case the index becomes too heavy, or it is not very accurate, but for now does the job.</p>

<h2 id="heading-notes">Notes</h2>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>The count of visible characters of the post’s text, as seen in the web browser, excluding white spaces. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">↩</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>See <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Big_O_notation" class="link-wikipedia">Big O Notation</a>. Also, technically, it has gone from O(1) to O(n m). <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">↩</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Web" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Static web sites are the best. They are fast, lightweight, safe and content-centric. However, not having a server comes with its sacrifices. I can go without forms, user accounts or comments, but the thing I miss the most is searching.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://lamaquinadeturing.su/search.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://lamaquinadeturing.su/search.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">“Cybernetics” (in A Dictionary of Philosophy, 1967)</title><link href="https://lamaquinadeturing.su/en/2024/07/cybernetics-in-a-Dictionary-of-philosophy-1967/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="“Cybernetics” (in A Dictionary of Philosophy, 1967)" /><published>2024-07-27T17:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-27T17:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://lamaquinadeturing.su/en/2024/07/cybernetics-in-a-Dictionary-of-philosophy-1967</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lamaquinadeturing.su/en/2024/07/cybernetics-in-a-Dictionary-of-philosophy-1967/"><![CDATA[<p><em>Cybernetics entry in</em> A Dictionary of Philosophy, <em>the influential work that reflected the political consensus in the USSR about many topics. This entry, probably based on the 1963 edition in Russian by Rozental and Yudin, reflects the post-Stalin view of cybernetics. Compare to <a href="/ca/2020/04/cibernetica-en-el-breu-diccionari-filosofic-1954/">this older entry</a> from a 1954 edition, where it is dubbed a “reactionary pseudoscience”, “mechanicist” and “idealist”. In contrast, in this edition cybernetics is “against” idealist philosophy.</em></p>

<hr>

<p><strong>Cybernetics</strong><sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>, the science of the common features of processes and control systems in technological devices, living organisms and human organisations. The principles of C. were first set forth by Wiener (q.v.). The emergence of C. as a science was prepared by a number of technological and scientific achievements in the theory of automatic control; electronics, which made possible the construction of fast-action scanning and programme-controlled computing devices; the theory of probability (q.v), notably its applications in investigating problems of transmission and processing of information (q.v.); mathematical logic (q.v.) and the theory of algorithms (see Algorism); the physiology of nervous activity and homeostasis. As distinct from devices that transform energy or substance, cybernetic systems engage in processing information. In the study of control systems C. combines the macroscopic with the microscopic approach. The macroscopic approach is employed when the internal structure of the system is not known and the only observable is the movement of information at its inputs and outputs (the information entering the system and the reaction of the system). In this way the main flows of information and the ultimate functions of the control system are established. This type of problem is known as the “black box” problem. The microscopic approach assumes a certain knowledge of the internal structure of the control system and involves the determination of its basic elements in their intertelationship, their algorithms of work and the possibility of synthetising a control system out of these elements. One of the central problems of C. is that of the structure of self-organising (self-adjusting) systems. These are complex control systems usually comprising hierarchies of interacting subsystems capable of maintaining or attaining certain states (or characteristics of their states) against external factors tending to disturb or hinder those states. The most perfect self-organising systems have developed as a result of evolutionary processes in animate nature. That is why C. makes use of analogies between control functions in living organisms and technological devices. The importance of C. is seen primarily in the light of the opportunities it opens up for the automation of production and all types of formalised human mental activity, the investigation of biological control and regulation systems (hormonal, neural, hereditary mechanisms) by the method of analogue simulation (q.v.), and the development of new types of medical apparatus. Another promising domain is the application of cybernetic methods to economic studies and other spheres of organised human activity. This great diversity of applications of cybernetic methods is not due to any subjective whims and wills; its objective foundation is the existence of certain common features in the functions and structures of living organisms and man-made devices capable of mathematical description and investigation. Being in this respect a synthetic discipline, C. offers a striking example of a new type of interaction of sciences and provides abundant material for the philosophical investigation of the forms of motion of matter and the classification of sciences. The development of C. sparked debates on a number of methodological problems, viz., the analogies between human thinking and the workings of cybernetic mechanisms, the nature of information and its connection with the physical concept of entropy (q.v.), the essence of what is called organised, purposeful, and living, and other problems of an indubitably philosophical nature around which a struggle between dialectical materialism and idealism has developed. Thus, idealist philosophy, which rejects the possibility of objective investigation of mental activity, comes out against the findings of C. which contribute to an understanding of certain important aspects and mechanisms of such activity. While recognising the objective soundness of cybernetic analogies, dialectical materialism at the same time emphasises the erroneousness of completely identifying man with a machine and human intelligence with the functioning of cybernetic systems.</p>

<hr>

<h2 id="heading-notes">Notes</h2>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>A Dictionary of Philosophy. Ed. in Russian M. Rozental and P. Yudin, ed. in English R. R. Dixon and M. Saifulin. Moscow, Progress, 1967, p. 108-109. <a href="https://archive.org/details/dictionaryphilosophy1967/" class="link-archive">Archived</a>. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">↩</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Cybernetics" /><category term="Lzhenauka" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Cybernetics entry in A Dictionary of Philosophy, the influential work that reflected the political consensus in the USSR about many topics. This entry, probably based on the 1963 edition in Russian by Rozental and Yudin, reflects the post-Stalin view of cybernetics. Compare to this older entry from a 1954 edition, where it is dubbed a “reactionary pseudoscience”, “mechanicist” and “idealist”. In contrast, in this edition cybernetics is “against” idealist philosophy.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://lamaquinadeturing.su/a-dictionary-of-philosophy.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://lamaquinadeturing.su/a-dictionary-of-philosophy.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry xml:lang="es"><title type="html">Cibernética – al servicio del comunismo</title><link href="https://lamaquinadeturing.su/es/2020/05/cibernetica-al-servicio-del-comunismo/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cibernética – al servicio del comunismo" /><published>2020-05-01T11:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-01T11:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://lamaquinadeturing.su/es/2020/05/cibernetica-al-servicio-del-comunismo</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lamaquinadeturing.su/es/2020/05/cibernetica-al-servicio-del-comunismo/"><![CDATA[<p><em>El siguiente texto es una traducción de la introducción al primer volumen de “Cibernética – al servicio del comunismo”, editado por Aksel I. Berg en 1961 en la URSS después de la restauración política de esta disciplina científica, <a href="/es/2020/04/cibernetica-en-el-breve-diccionario-filosofico-1954/">antes demonizada por el estalinismo</a>.</em></p>

<p><em>Esta serie de libros contenían las actas del seminario organizado por Berg y otros cibernetistas, en el cual discutían los aspectos cientifico-técnicos de esta nueva disciplina y a la vez buscaban un cuerpo teórico adecuado a los principios comunistas.</em></p>

<p><em>La introducción repasa los artículos de una veintena de autores, en un texto que muestra el interés de los investigadores soviéticos por temas que hoy en día son de plena actualidad: el diagnóstico automatizado de enfermedades usando</em> big data, <em>aprendizaje automático</em> (machine learning), <em>lectura de textos y reconocimiento de voz, teoría de colas, teoría de la información, sistemas tolerantes a fallos y autoregenerativos, etc., incluso la aplicación a procesos legales. Esto por sí solo desmonta los mitos neoliberales que vinculan creatividad e innovación al lucro personal, demostrando que el progreso científico-técnico no es propio del capitalismo, y existe más allá de la figura del</em> emprendedor.</p>

<p><em>De Berg, trasluce su visión de una ciencia al servicio de la vida y las humanidades (que en ningún momento se contemplan como contrapuestas a la ciencia, como ocurre hoy en día), a favor de la colaboración científica internacional, y destaca sensibilidad ecologista por la contaminación y sus efectos en humanos y ecosistemas.</em></p>

<p><em>En definitiva, es un documento que muestra los usos que se podría haber dado a la tecnología cibernética, y que hoy estamos a tiempo de dar a la tecnología informática.</em></p>

<hr>

<h2 id="heading-introducción">Introducción</h2>

<p><strong>A. I. Berg</strong></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Es necesario organizar un uso generalizado de la cibernética, la informática electrónica y los dispositivos de control en la producción, la investigación y el desarrollo, la práctica del diseño de los cálculos de planificación, en el campo de la contabilidad, la estadística y la gestión.</p>

  <p>Del proyecto de Programa del PCUS</p>
</blockquote>

<p>El borrador del Programa de nuestro partido indica que la sociedad comunista, en contraste con todas las formaciones socioeconómicas anteriores, no se forma espontáneamente, sino como resultado de la actividad consciente y decidida de las masas lideradas por el partido marxista-leninista. El liderazgo del partido en la construcción del comunismo se basa en el conocimiento de las leyes de desarrollo de la sociedad, y esto le da un carácter organizado, planificado y científicamente sólido.</p>

<p>Estas disposiciones fundamentales en las que se basan todas nuestras actividades científicas y prácticas son de gran importancia: son el resultado de estudiar toda la práctica de construir el socialismo en nuestro país durante los últimos años. Ahora nos muestran, después de más de 40 años, cuán perspicaz fue V.I. Lenin, buscando desde los primeros días de la revolución llevar la base científica a las medidas prácticas del gobierno soviético en la organización, planificación y dirección de la gestión de la economía nacional de un país que acababa de salir de una sangrienta y guerra devastadora. En marzo – abril de 1918, Vladimir Ilich Lenin hizo un artículo importante, “Las tareas inmediatas del gobierno soviético”. En este artículo, dijo:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Nosotros, el partido bolchevique, convencimos a Rusia. Hemos conquistado Rusia: de los ricos para los pobres, de los explotadores para los trabajadores. Ahora debemos gestionar Rusia. Y toda la singularidad del momento que se experimenta, toda la dificultad es comprender las características de la transición de la tarea principal de persuadir al pueblo y la supresión militar de los explotadores a la tarea principal de la gestión”.</p>

  <p>Obras completas<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>, 4ª ed., vol. 27, p. 214</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Las tremendas dificultades para combatir la devastación, el sabotaje de la burguesía y la burocracia, el hambre y la falta de las cosas más necesarias en el país, el desvío de todas las fuerzas hacia la guerra civil y la lucha de los intervencionistas no impidieron que V. I. Lenin volviera a este tema una vez más en 1920 durante la discusión sobre El papel de los sindicatos.</p>

<p>Finalmente, en 1923, en su último artículo “Mejor poco, pero mejor” (Pravda<sup id="fnref:2" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>, 4 de marzo), V. I. Lenin expresó su preocupación por la imperfección del aparato estatal de la joven república soviética y enfatizó la necesidad de estudiar “los fundamentos de la teoría sobre el tema de nuestro aparato estatal” y el conocimiento de <em>los fundamentos de la ciencia de gestión</em> (obras completas<sup id="fnref:1:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>, 4ª ed., vol. 27, p. 278).</p>

<p>Los años posteriores han demostrado y confirmado la corrección del énfasis de Lenin en el problema de gestión. Con el desarrollo de la economía nacional, las dificultades de su gestión racional crecieron constantemente. Al mismo tiempo, la práctica ha confirmado que es en una economía socialista planificada donde existen todas las condiciones para el mejor uso de los logros de la ciencia y la tecnología en beneficio de todos los miembros de la sociedad, y no de los grupos rivales individuales y la minoría privilegiada.</p>

<p>La Unión Soviética no se vio afectada por la crisis industrial de 1929-1932, que conmocionó profundamente al mundo capitalista y describió de manera particularmente vívida su anarquismo.</p>

<p>A pesar de las enormes pérdidas sufridas durante la guerra civil de 1918-1921, la industria de la Unión Soviética, que se estaba desarrollando rápidamente, alcanzó su nivel anterior a la guerra (1913) en 1925-1926. La tasa de crecimiento y el progreso de la economía socialista planificada resultaron ser tan altos que en 1941 el país resultó estar preparado para la guerra solo con uno de los países más industrializados del mundo: Alemania. Esto, por supuesto, fue el resultado de la mejora continua en la planificación y gestión de la economía nacional.</p>

<p>Durante la Segunda Guerra Mundial, los problemas de una mejor organización de la industria de defensa y una mejor gestión de las operaciones militares atrajeron la atención más seria. Aparecieron nuevas ciencias: la teoría de la investigación operativa, la teoría de los juegos matemáticos, la teoría del servicio de masas; Se dio un desarrollo significativo a la estadística matemática y la teoría de la probabilidad. La complicación continua y rápida del equipo militar y sus frecuentes fallas llamaron la atención sobre la falta de fiabilidad de los dispositivos y aparatos complejos de elementos múltiples. Se comenzó a trabajar sistemáticamente para crear una teoría matemática de la confiabilidad y para estudiar métodos y métodos tecnológicos para mantenerla a un alto nivel.</p>

<p>El rápido desarrollo de la electrónica y la instrumentación allanó el camino para la creación de los primeros medios de automatización electrónica y, finalmente, las primeras computadoras electrónicas. Las máquinas matemáticas y la automatización electrónica, a su vez, nos permitieron plantear un nuevo problema científico para mejorar la gestión de procesos y operaciones complejas. Así nació una nueva ciencia de la gestión: la cibernética.</p>

<p>En los últimos años, se han publicado muchos libros y artículos de revistas sobre cibernética en la literatura rusa y mundial. Hay trabajos científicos serios, cuya comprensión es accesible solo para especialistas bien entrenados y que trabajan en campos relativamente estrechos. Muchos buenos libros de no ficción se han escrito para un amplio público. A pesar de esto, la creciente demanda de literatura en el campo de la cibernética no se está cumpliendo. Este es un fenómeno completamente natural para nuestro tiempo. Se explica por el hecho de que una persona siente una creciente necesidad de aumentar la eficiencia de su trabajo, es decir, obtener ciertos resultados con el menor gasto de tiempo, trabajo, materiales y energía. Pueden objetarme que este deseo siempre ha existido. Sin embargo, no es difícil verificar que este no sea realmente el caso.</p>

<p>En los viejos tiempos, la actividad científica se limitaba a observar o recopilar información, como estamos acostumbrados a decir. Los resultados de las observaciones fueron memorizados, registrados y almacenados. Se crearon grandes bibliotecas, pero contenían principalmente material descriptivo. Catálogos, clasificaciones, sistemas fueron compilados. Pero hubo pocos intentos de penetrar más profundamente en la esencia y la interconexión de los fenómenos observados, principalmente porque el aparato matemático a disposición de los científicos, así como los medios y equipos técnicos, no correspondían en absoluto a la complejidad de los fenómenos y procesos que se estudian.</p>

<p>La experiencia cotidiana convenció a nuestros ancestros distantes de su debilidad e impotencia en los intentos de someter a las fuerzas de la naturaleza. El miedo a las fuerzas omnipotentes de la naturaleza, generado por esta impotencia, acostumbró al hombre a la sumisión a su destino, a la pasividad, a la superstición. La ciencia se desarrolló lentamente porque todas las fuerzas del hombre fueron absorbidas por la lucha por la existencia, y había una sensación de la necesidad de establecer relaciones de causa y efecto, para explicar los hechos observados. De los “científicos” se esperaba solo un beneficio: la profecía. y predicciones Fue un período de astrología en astronomía y medicina en medicina. Los intentos de pensamiento independiente que no encajaban en los cánones legalizados se consideraron sacrilegio y terminaron en una hoguera.</p>

<p>¿Quizás todo esto fue mucho tiempo y ahora no hay nada que recordar al respecto? Desafortunadamente, la situación descrita anteriormente existió hasta los últimos siglos, es decir, durante cientos de miles de años, porque las primeras personas aparecieron en la Tierra hace un millón de años, y los primeros rudimentos de la civilización, en sus formas más primitivas, aparecieron solo unos 10 mil años. volver Las últimas hogueras se apagaron hace 135 años… La ciencia moderna nació en los primeros trabajos de Leibniz y Newton en matemáticas superiores. Solo desde la introducción del cálculo diferencial e integral en la ciencia podemos hablar sobre el surgimiento de las ciencias naturales modernas, ya que la oportunidad se ha abierto para la transición de características “descriptivas” y cualitativas al establecimiento de leyes matemáticas, cuantitativas exactas y, por lo tanto, no solo para indicar fenómenos y hechos, sino también e intenta intervenir activamente en los fenómenos del mundo exterior.</p>

<p>El éxito de esta intervención llevó a la idea de su viabilidad y dio lugar a la necesidad de desarrollar un trabajo científico que conduzca al logro de objetivos específicos de la vida práctica.</p>

<p>Una persona comenzó a fortalecer su creencia en sus habilidades y capacidades. Se plantearon y resolvieron las tareas cada vez más difíciles de aumentar la productividad del trabajo físico. Desde los dispositivos y mecanismos más simples, el hombre cambió a máquinas. La capacidad de producir y mantener el fuego, adquirida hace 30-40 mil años, se utilizó hace 200 años para crear las primeras máquinas de vapor, y comenzó la era de la mecanización de máquinas. Actualmente, el 99% de todo el trabajo útil llevado a cabo en la Tierra se lleva a cabo mediante máquinas controladas por humanos y solo el 1%, por fuerza física no mecanizada. Pero esto no significa en absoluto que solo el uno por ciento de los trabajadores en el mundo se dedique a trabajos físicos no mecanizados. En nuestro país, por ejemplo, según datos poco precisos, del 40 al 60% de los trabajadores están empleados en trabajos auxiliares, principalmente no mecanizados, y esto incluye principalmente la carga y descarga. Pero un trabajador con nosotros, que controla una máquina o una máquina, realiza un trabajo útil, más de cientos de trabajadores que se dedican a un trabajo físico simple. En promedio, en el mundo, dada la baja mecanización de los países subdesarrollados, el porcentaje de trabajadores que manejan máquinas es mucho más bajo que en la URSS, y representa solo un pequeño porcentaje. Sin embargo, es precisamente este número insignificante de trabajadores calificados los que realizan la mayor parte (99%) del trabajo útil en la Tierra.</p>

<p>Cabe recordar que hace unos 100 años la imagen era completamente diferente: aproximadamente el 4% de todo el trabajo útil fue realizado por máquinas y el 96% por trabajo físico, manual. La mecanización y la maquinización comenzaron a extenderse rápidamente solo a fines del siglo pasado después de la invención y el uso generalizado de dinamos, corriente alterna, su sistema de líneas de alta tensión [канализации] y el uso de motores eléctricos y motores eléctricos. La energía eléctrica, su generación, distribución y conversión en energía mecánica revolucionó la industria a fines del siglo XX.</p>

<p>El uso científico e industrial de la electricidad ha abierto nuevas oportunidades no solo para aumentar la capacidad energética de la mano de obra: los dispositivos y los controles de automatización han comenzado a ser ampliamente utilizados. Pero esto se aplica a nuestro siglo, más precisamente, a nuestro tiempo. No debe haber conceptos erróneos: la era de la automatización apenas comienza.</p>

<p>La automatización con medios neumáticos, hidráulicos y electromecánicos ha existido durante varias décadas. Pero la automatización moderna comenzó después de la llegada de los dispositivos electrónicos, de vacío y semiconductores. Las lámparas electrónicas se utilizaron ampliamente en la ingeniería de radio hace 40 años, y en la electrónica industrial y la automatización electrónica hace solo 10 años.</p>

<p>Los dispositivos electrónicos de semiconductores son aún más jóvenes. Comenzaron a encontrar un uso generalizado durante no más de 7-8 años. Pero el ritmo de su distribución, incluso para nuestro tiempo, es sorprendente: en la actualidad, al menos varios cientos de millones de dispositivos semiconductores se producen en el mundo por año.</p>

<p>Pronto su lanzamiento alcanzará los mil millones al año, y reemplazarán las lámparas electrónicas en muchas áreas.</p>

<p>Al final de la Segunda Guerra Mundial, se desarrollaron las primeras computadoras electrónicas. Tomó varios años mejorarlos. Desde 1952, es decir, hace unos 10 años, comenzó una nueva era en matemáticas, electrónica, automatización y en todas las ramas del conocimiento basadas en estas ciencias. Finalmente, fue posible plantear y resolver el problema de un aumento significativo en la efectividad del trabajo mental. Casi al mismo tiempo, nació una nueva ciencia, la cibernética, la ciencia de la gestión.</p>

<p>Ahora podemos volver al comienzo de nuestra introducción. Hemos demostrado con ejemplos concretos que solo en los últimos años se ha abierto la posibilidad de plantear conscientemente el problema de aumentar la eficiencia del trabajo humano en todas las áreas de su actividad. Ahora podemos estudiar fenómenos en la naturaleza viva, procesos de producción en la industria y operaciones realizadas por personas en la sociedad humana, utilizando métodos científicos y medios técnicos correspondientes a la complejidad y sutileza de estos fenómenos, procesos y acciones.</p>

<p>Pero ahora este estudio tiene objetivos prácticos. Ahora no estamos completamente satisfechos con la contemplación, observación, medición y almacenamiento de esta información. En el estudio del mundo que nos rodea y de la vida silvestre necesitamos utilizar esta información para satisfacer las necesidades materiales y espirituales del hombre, para facilitar su trabajo.</p>

<hr class="asterisks">

<p>El primer volumen de la colección “Cibernética: al servicio del comunismo” contiene varios artículos cuyo propósito es familiarizar a los lectores con las oportunidades que surgen en el uso práctico de los principios de la cibernética. La colección contiene, además de la introducción, 19 artículos escritos por autores que trabajan directamente en los campos relevantes. Los artículos se agrupan en 4 secciones: la primera sección: recopilación, procesamiento y transmisión de información; segunda cibernética y vida silvestre; la tercera es cibernética y humanidades, y la cuarta sección es cibernética en ciencia y tecnología.</p>

<p>A continuación resumimos brevemente el contenido de cada artículo en estas secciones.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“En el siglo de rápido desarrollo de la ciencia, el desarrollo de problemas filosóficos de la ciencia natural moderna sobre la base del materialismo dialéctico como la única visión científica mundial y método de cognición se vuelve aún más urgente”.</p>

  <p>Del borrador del nuevo Programa del PCUS</p>
</blockquote>

<p>La cibernética es una nueva ciencia que se está generalizando. Afirma estudiar los procesos de gestión que tienen lugar en la naturaleza viva, en la producción y en la sociedad humana, es decir, para cubrir casi todas las actividades humanas, y por lo tanto tenemos el derecho de exigir que los fundamentos ideológicos sobre los que se desarrolla esta ciencia en nuestro país impecable Desde los primeros días de la revolución, V. I. Lenin estuvo muy involucrado en la ciencia de la gobernanza. A lo largo de los años de existencia del poder soviético, se ha prestado mucha atención a estos problemas en la URSS. Pero la cibernética como ciencia del manejo de sistemas dinámicos complejos, basada en la base matemática y el uso de dispositivos electrónicos modernos, se originó en Occidente, y uno de sus fundadores es el matemático estadounidense Norbert Wiener. En este sentido, las ideas, pensamientos y generalizaciones bastante razonables y progresistas contenidos en los trabajos modernos sobre cibernética a veces se presentan a los lectores desde posiciones ideológicas poco claras, contradictorias y a menudo erróneas, lo que trae un daño significativo. La tarea de los científicos soviéticos es crear la escuela soviética de cibernética, basada en el materialismo dialéctico.</p>

<p>En los últimos años, hemos hecho mucho, en esta área. Puede referirse, por ejemplo, a la colección recientemente publicada de Cuestiones filosóficas de la cibernética. Pero estamos lejos de pensar que los artículos de esta colección agotan todo el problema. Por lo tanto, en ‘esta colección es un artículo de I. B. Novik “Sobre algunos problemas metodológicos de la cibernética”. Habla sobre la optimización de la gestión, la naturaleza de la información, la relación entre el hombre y la máquina, y la naturaleza de la cibernética como ciencia. Estamos seguros de que la publicación de este interesante artículo en nuestra colección fortalecerá aún más los fundamentos ideológicos de la cibernética.</p>

<h3 id="heading-i-recogida-tratamiento-y-transferencia-de-información">I. RECOGIDA, TRATAMIENTO Y TRANSFERENCIA DE INFORMACIÓN</h3>

<p>En la primera sección, cuyos artículos proporcionan información sobre la recopilación, el procesamiento y la transmisión de información, el miembro de la Academia de Ciencias de la RSS de Ucrania, prof. B.V. Gnedenko, habla sobre algunos temas de cibernética y estadísticas. En 1956, B.V. Gnedenko, N. M. Amosov, E. A. Shkabara y sus empleados se interesaron en los problemas del diagnóstico médico y llevaron a cabo uno de los primeros intentos en el mundo para el procesamiento estadístico de material clínico, sobre la base de lo cual generalmente se hace el diagnóstico, y se utilizó una computadora electrónica para estos fines. Esto hizo posible obtener evaluaciones más objetivas de varios conjuntos de síntomas que los que puede hacer un médico. El uso de métodos de estadística matemática, lógica matemática y teoría de la probabilidad en el desarrollo de un diagnóstico en el futuro ayudará significativamente a los médicos.</p>

<p>El autor habla sobre la importancia de utilizar los métodos de la teoría del servicio de masas en la organización de la producción. Desde la creación de las primeras centrales telefónicas a principios de este siglo, se sabe que el científico danés A. K. Erlang tiene el mérito de haber desarrollado los fundamentos de esta ciencia matemática. Esta teoría examina los problemas de evaluar la calidad del “servicio” de un determinado sistema en el que es inevitable esperar su turno y determinar el tiempo promedio de “servicio”. Esta teoría considera, por ejemplo, el problema del servicio racional de pasajeros en las taquillas de ferrocarriles, en las empresas comerciales, al calcular las vías de acceso de fábricas, amarres de puertos, lugares de aterrizaje de aviones, etc. El artículo describe un caso interesante de cálculo de silos que acumulan existencias de productos durante la producción en línea, proporciona información sobre algunos problemas de fiabilidad estadística (es decir, tiempo de actividad) de los sistemas de control que consisten en una gran cantidad de elementos, cada uno de los cuales se caracteriza por su probabilidad inherente de un funcionamiento adecuado.</p>

<p>En una forma accesible para el lector general, pero al mismo tiempo bastante seria, B.V. Gpedenko muestra cómo las matemáticas “puras” ayudan a resolver los problemas prácticos reales de nuestro tiempo, qué papel juegan ramas relativamente nuevas de las matemáticas en esto, como la teoría de la planificación óptima, la teoría juegos, teoría de procesos aleatorios, etc.</p>

<p>La cibernética se basa en la recopilación, el procesamiento y la entrega de información. La información es también un concepto básico de la teoría general de la comunicación. Mientras tanto, el término “información” en sí no tiene una definición exacta.<sup id="fnref:3" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote" rel="footnote">3</a></sup> Esto no debería confundirnos, ya que para la investigación y las actividades prácticas y para el desarrollo posterior de la teoría del control, realmente no necesitamos definiciones precisas de ciertos conceptos. Después de todo, no sabemos qué es el tiempo, nadie puede dar una definición de esta palabra, pero lo medimos perfectamente con gran precisión y lo ponemos en la base de todos nuestros cálculos de eficiencia, productividad laboral. Hablamos de desperdicio y la necesidad de ahorrar tiempo, el uso indebido del tiempo es punible en algunos casos por ley… Tampoco sabemos qué es el espacio, pero lo medimos, utilizamos los teoremas de la geometría: la ciencia del espacio. Se puede discutir con esto, pero es poco probable que alguien, excepto algunos filósofos y matemáticos que se dedican especialmente a este problema, pueda satisfacer el concepto generalizado del espacio como una colección continua de cualquier objeto o fenómeno homogéneo, la medición de distancias en la que se lleva a cabo de acuerdo con cualquier ley con pasos infinitesimales (Riemann, 1854). Hay muchos ejemplos similares. Pero esto no interfiere con nuestras actividades científicas y prácticas que ocurren en el tiempo y el espacio…</p>

<p>Los méritos del científico e ingeniero de comunicaciones estadounidense Shannon y muchos otros científicos soviéticos y extranjeros, que sentaron las bases de la teoría general de la comunicación y la teoría matemática, más precisamente, probabilística y de información estadística, son bien conocidos. La aplicabilidad de las disposiciones de la teoría del ego a los problemas de transmisión de información a través de canales inanimados no está en duda. Los intentos de extenderlo a los organismos vivos aún no han dado un resultado positivo, y quizás en este caso es necesario utilizar categorías completamente diferentes. Nos parece que la colección “Teoría de la información en biología”, que fue publicada en la URSS en 1960 por la Editorial de Literatura Extranjera, es de considerable interés a este respecto.</p>

<p>Nuestra colección contiene un artículo de R. L. Dobrushin y Y. I. Khurtin, “Preguntas en la teoría de la información”. Interesará a los lectores planteando algunas preguntas, aunque leer este artículo requiere cierta preparación matemática. Los autores están tratando de formular y explicar algunos problemas de codificación óptima de la información, y nos parece que tuvieron éxito. La literatura sobre teoría de la información es muy significativa. Los autores enumeran una serie de trabajos que merecen atención a la luz de los problemas que están considerando. Es interesante notar que en el apéndice del <em><a href="https://ca.wikipedia.org/wiki/IRE" class="link-wikipedia">Institute of Radio Engineers</a> <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IEEE_Transactions_on_Information_Theory" class="link-wikipedia">Transactions on Information Theory</a></em>, nº 2, junio de 1956, contiene <a href="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/1056783" class="link-external">“Una bibliografía de literatura soviética sobre la teoría de la información, correlación y ruido”</a>, compilada en los EEUU, que contiene alrededor de 150 títulos. En el segundo volumen de nuestra colección, tenemos la intención de imprimir varios artículos sobre información interpretada desde el punto de vista de la cibernética teórica. Estos incluyen, por ejemplo, los problemas de percepción y reconocimiento de imágenes en la naturaleza viva. Estos problemas atraen cada vez más la atención de psicólogos y fisiólogos, así como de especialistas en máquinas electrónicas que trabajan en el campo del autoaprendizaje y autoajuste. Hasta cierto punto, estos problemas se plantean en un artículo de A. V. Napalkov, colocado en la segunda sección de esta colección.</p>

<p>Dado que el procesamiento de la información es la base de la gestión, se imprime en la colección un artículo de K. B. Arutyunov y D. V. Svecharnik “Selección, procesamiento primario, almacenamiento y transmisión de información sobre el curso de los procesos de producción”. Considera las peculiaridades de la actividad de información en la producción en comparación con los organismos vivos. Se destaca y explica la conveniencia excepcional de todo el mecanismo y dispositivo para transmitir información y su almacenamiento en organismos vivos. Es especialmente importante mantener la alta confiabilidad de estos procesos. En la vida silvestre, esto está garantizado por la interacción de todos los elementos estructurales y funcionales involucrados en este proceso. Gracias a esto, durante millones de años, por medio de la selección natural y la adaptación a las condiciones ambientales, esas especies han sobrevivido en las que el trabajo conjunto de una gran cantidad de elementos menos confiables garantiza una confiabilidad extremadamente alta. Desafortunadamente, la lucha por mejorar la confiabilidad de los instrumentos, herramientas y sistemas de recopilación, almacenamiento y procesamiento de datos que deben usarse en la industria apenas está comenzando, y la situación en esta área aún debe ser reconocida como insatisfactoria. Las preguntas planteadas en el artículo anterior son muy relevantes. Planeamos en el segundo volumen, en 1962, desarrollar significativamente la sección de información y, en particular, colocar varios artículos sobre instrumentación científica, ya que el equipo de laboratorios científicos con estos dispositivos que no satisface las necesidades limita sus capacidades, reduciendo la efectividad del trabajo experimental de investigación de nuestros científicos.</p>

<p>La primera sección contiene un artículo de K. Ya. Sergeychuk, “Problemas de comunicación y cibernética”. El autor muestra el creciente papel de la ciencia de las comunicaciones y su tecnología en el rápido desarrollo de la economía nacional de nuestro país. Se destaca el papel creciente de los sistemas con alto rendimiento, en particular los enlaces coaxiales y de microondas. Ahora podemos agregarles las capacidades recientemente descubiertas de transmisión direccional intensa [резко] de una gran cantidad de información sobre ondas electromagnéticas de los rangos infrarrojo y óptico. Aquí se abren grandes oportunidades, de las cuales solo una parte ha sido tenida en cuenta. Los generadores y amplificadores de mecánica cuántica de este rango de longitud de onda permiten crear receptores de alta sensibilidad y bajo nivel de ruido, en los cuales la comunicación por radio se llevará a cabo a distancias de escala astronómica (varios años luz). Se abren oportunidades para construir máquinas electrónicas con gran velocidad. Probablemente, estas nuevas perspectivas nos harán re-evaluar la importancia de algunos de los sistemas modernos de transferencia de información.</p>

<p>K. Ya. Serteychuk habla más sobre el papel y la importancia de las comunicaciones en la automatización de la economía nacional, cuando los dispositivos automáticos y las máquinas electrónicas resultan ser fuentes y receptores de información. En este sentido, el término “comunicación tecnológica” [технологическая связь] comienza a utilizarse, que se entiende como un complejo de medios técnicos de comunicación que proporcionan control de la producción automatizada. Observamos de paso que estos temas también se abordan en los artículos de A. I. Kitov y V. A. Ilyin, ubicados en las secciones tercera y cuarta de la colección.</p>

<p>Finalmente, el artículo llama la atención sobre la creciente importancia de una mayor elaboración de los problemas de la teoría de la información y el uso de máquinas electrónicas para el procesamiento de la información. En este artículo se presta especial y merecida atención a la creciente importancia de la robotización confiable de los medios automatizados de transmisión de información.</p>

<h3 id="heading-ii-cibernética-y-naturaleza-viva">II. CIBERNÉTICA Y NATURALEZA VIVA</h3>

<p>Estamos principalmente interesados en la vida silvestre, la flora y la fauna. Y, sobre todo, nos preocupamos por la persona, por su salud. La sociedad comunista debe ser construida por personas sanas. El mantenimiento de la salud, la prevención de enfermedades, el diagnóstico precoz de enfermedades graves, los métodos de tratamiento eficaces en caso de enfermedad es la principal preocupación de las autoridades sanitarias soviéticas. La mejora integral de la mano de obra, la introducción de medios modernos de seguridad técnica y la provisión de condiciones sanitarias y técnicas que eliminen las lesiones y enfermedades profesionales son la principal preocupación de nuestro partido para el hombre soviético, como se establece en el proyecto de Programa del PCUS. Es interesante recordar que la misma preocupación se mostró en 1919. El segundo programa del partido, adoptado en el 8º Congreso del PCR, dijo: “En el campo de la salud pública, la adopción decisiva de amplias medidas sanitarias en interés de los trabajadores, tales como: a) mejora áreas pobladas (protección del suelo, agua, aire)”, etc.</p>

<p>Lamentablemente, la industrialización va acompañada de la contaminación de nuestro medio ambiente. Las preguntas planteadas hace más de 40 años aún no se han resuelto en la medida en que esto es necesario. Las potentes centrales térmicas son una fuente de contaminación del aire si no se toman medidas para limpiar el humo. La tecnología moderna nos permite hacer esto, y estas oportunidades deben ser aprovechadas, de lo contrario las poderosas estaciones termales se convertirán en fuentes de envenenamiento del aire y muerte de la vegetación. ¿Se presta suficiente atención a este grave problema? Según nuestra información, no. El envenenamiento del suelo y el agua por parte de las empresas industriales sigue siendo un problema sin resolver, ya que la industria crece y se desarrolla más rápido de lo que se implementan las medidas preventivas y de prohibición.</p>

<p>Se ha publicado un extenso material sobre todos estos temas en el mundo y en nuestra prensa, pero las tareas, en mi opinión, todavía no se resuelven satisfactoriamente. Se necesita un cambio radical aquí. Esto es exactamente lo que requiere el párrafo del borrador del Programa:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Se están produciendo cambios importantes en el desarrollo de todo el complejo de ciencias biológicas en relación con las necesidades de resolver con éxito los problemas de la medicina y el desarrollo de la agricultura. Los intereses de la humanidad plantean ante estas ciencias como tareas principales la clarificación de la esencia de los fenómenos de la vida, el dominio y la gestión de los procesos de la vida, en particular, el metabolismo, la herencia de los organismos. La ciencia médica debe centrarse en el descubrimiento de medios para prevenir y superar enfermedades.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Parece que la preocupación por la salud del pueblo soviético no pertenece al tema de esta colección, pero en realidad no es así.</p>

<p>Uno de los documentos más importantes que caracterizan esta situación es la resolución del Comité Central del PCUS y el Consejo de Ministros de la URSS del 14 de enero de 1960 “Sobre medidas para mejorar aún más los servicios médicos y proteger la salud de la población del país”. De acuerdo con las grandes oportunidades creadas recientemente por la ciencia y la tecnología, esta resolución enumera muchas actividades cuya implementación permitirá utilizar ampliamente los logros en el campo de la instrumentación y la electrónica en las instituciones médicas. La resolución propone ampliar significativamente el trabajo de investigación y desarrollo en la creación de equipos médicos basados ​​en el uso de los logros modernos en biología, química, física nuclear, electrónica y cibernética. Se presta especial atención al desarrollo de máquinas y dispositivos de diagnóstico especiales para la evaluación precisa de los cambios funcionales y morfológicos en el cuerpo en función de los últimos logros de la cibernética. Los médicos de diagnóstico tendrán la oportunidad de establecer las causas y la naturaleza de la enfermedad mediante el análisis de los síntomas que, sin máquinas electrónicas, corren el riesgo de no ser detectados, y así garantizar que el diagnóstico se realice en una etapa más temprana de la enfermedad grave que la que se está haciendo actualmente.</p>

<p>Todas estas instrucciones de nuestro partido y nuestro gobierno se están implementando actualmente. Para resolver los problemas difíciles asociados con estos problemas, participan matemáticos, especialistas en electrónica y biología. Docenas de colectivos ahora trabajan en este problema en Moscú, Leningrado, Kiev, Tbilisi y otras ciudades de la URSS, en los países de democracia popular, así como en Occidente. Sobre los problemas del uso de las matemáticas, la electrónica y la cibernética en biología y medicina, se ha publicado una extensa literatura científica, que en 1961 tiene al menos cinco mil artículos. Los congresos y reuniones internacionales están dedicados a este tema. En todas partes se están tomando medidas para capacitar a especialistas en electrónica biológica, este nuevo tipo de médico, ingeniero y electricista. En 1961, se celebró una conferencia científica sobre el uso de la cibernética en la cirugía en el Instituto de Cirugía A. V. Vishnevsky. Por iniciativa del director de este instituto, el Instituto A. A. Vishnevsky estableció un laboratorio de cibernética médica. Médicos e ingenieros, fisiólogos y matemáticos, radiólogos y técnicos trabajan en él.</p>

<p>En 1959, se celebró una conferencia científica en Moscú sobre el uso de la electrónica en biología y medicina. Se escucharon varias docenas de informes interesantes al respecto, y se demostró el equipo original. Los trabajos de la conferencia se publicaron en la colección <em>Electrónica en la medicina</em>, Gosenergoizdat<sup id="fnref:4" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote" rel="footnote">4</a></sup>, 1960. En 1962, se convocará una segunda conferencia sobre el mismo tema.</p>

<p>Permítanme recordarle al lector que la electrónica biológica y la cibernética tienen solo unos pocos años de vida. Todo lo que se ha hecho hasta ahora es solo el comienzo de una nueva era en biología, y los científicos de la Unión Soviética y otros países lo saben. No cabe duda de que los próximos años abrirán perspectivas y oportunidades completamente nuevas.</p>

<p>El artículo “Cibernética y vida”, publicado en el “Ekonomicheskoy gazete”<sup id="fnref:5" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:5" class="footnote" rel="footnote">5</a></sup> el 12 de junio de 1960, enumera algunas áreas de aplicación de la cibernética en biología. Estos incluyen: el estudio de varios procesos de control en la naturaleza viva, las células vivas, el comportamiento de los seres vivos, la evolución de la vida silvestre en su conjunto, el diagnóstico, el manejo de ciertos procesos fisiológicos, el estudio de los fenómenos de herencia y la influencia directa en estos procesos para derivar formas valiosas de animales, plantas y microorganismos, etc.</p>

<p>¿Qué es característico de todo este nuevo campo de la ciencia? La biología se caracteriza por la tendencia centenaria de acumular información sobre organismos vivos. El material recolectado durante 5-6 mil años es enorme. Pero, ¿a qué métodos iba a recurrir, qué medios técnicos se utilizaron para estudiar los fenómenos y procesos más complejos conocidos en el mundo? Es cierto que el lento progreso de la biología no se puede culpar a un solo biólogo. No hay duda de que las ciencias técnicas, que no proporcionaron a los biólogos los medios para estudiar, recopilar y analizar información, son igualmente culpables de esto o incluso más. ¿Qué podría haber puesto la tecnología a disposición de los biólogos antes del siglo XX? Solo los medios inadecuados para un estudio serio de las leyes más complejas de la naturaleza viva, hasta que la ingeniería eléctrica y la electrónica posterior no cambiaron su posición mediante el desarrollo de electrocardiógrafos, espectroscopía de radio de microondas, microscopios electrónicos, rayos X, encefalografías, etc. En ninguna parte, en ninguna área de la actividad humana durante miles de años, ha habido tal desajuste entre los medios científicos y técnicos de la complejidad y los fenómenos y procesos estudiados. La aplicación de métodos matemáticos en biología, incluso para procesar los resultados de las observaciones (estadísticas matemáticas), hasta las últimas décadas se consideraba casi una blasfemia. Y esto sucedió, a pesar de que los fundadores del marxismo-leninismo y el materialismo dialéctico hablaron muy definitivamente sobre este tema.</p>

<p>En la “Dialéctica de la naturaleza” F. Engels dice:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Solo el cálculo diferencial permite a las ciencias naturales representar matemáticamente no solo estados, sino también procesos: movimiento</p>

  <p>Gospolitizdat<sup id="fnref:6" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:6" class="footnote" rel="footnote">6</a></sup>, 1952, p. 218</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Lafargue en sus memorias cita la declaración de Marx de que “la ciencia solo alcanza la perfección cuando logra usar las matemáticas” (P. Lafargue, Memorias de Marx, en la colección “Memorias de Marx y Engels”, Gospolitizdat<sup id="fnref:6:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:6" class="footnote" rel="footnote">6</a></sup>, 1956, p. 66).</p>

<p>Nuestro mejor científico, acad.<sup id="fnref:7" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:7" class="footnote" rel="footnote">7</a></sup> I. P. Pavlov dice:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>…toda la vida, desde los organismos más simples hasta los más complejos, incluidos, por supuesto, los humanos, existe una larga serie de equilibrios ambientales cada vez más complejos que se vuelven cada vez más complicados. Llegará el momento, aunque distante, cuando el análisis matemático, basado en las ciencias naturales, ilumine todos estos equilibrios con magníficas fórmulas de ecuaciones…</p>

  <p>Obras completas, vol. III, libro 1, pp. 124-125</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Estos ejemplos podrían continuar. Si recordamos que estas declaraciones pertenecían a las primeras etapas de la introducción de las matemáticas en las ciencias naturales y la biología, entonces la instrumentación, la ingeniería eléctrica y la informática estaban en un nivel bajo, que nadie podría haber previsto las enormes oportunidades que la electrónica tenía para abrir, y en especialmente su simbiosis con las matemáticas, la creación de la automatización electrónica y las máquinas matemáticas electrónicas, y aún más la nueva ciencia del procesamiento de la información en estas máquinas—la cibernética, es necesario rendir homenaje al don de previsión de las personas avanzadas del pasado en la evaluación correcta de las perspectivas distantes de la ciencia y, en particular, de las matemáticas aplicadas.</p>

<p>Vivimos en la era de la matematización de todas las ciencias naturales y humanas, y la matematización de la biología es solo uno de los lados de este proceso.</p>

<p>Esta colección contiene artículos de A. D. Voskresensky y A. I. Prokhorov sobre el uso de la cibernética en biología y medicina. Desarrollaron las consideraciones anteriores. En el artículo del prof. S. N. Braines sobre neurocibernética aborda cuestiones que han comenzado a desarrollarse en la URSS recientemente. Los resultados de estos interesantes estudios se presentan en un libro sobre neurocibernética<sup id="fnref:8" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:8" class="footnote" rel="footnote">8</a></sup> (a finales de 1961 se publicará su segunda edición ampliada) y también se consideraron en varios congresos internacionales.</p>

<p>De considerable interés es el artículo de A. V. Napalkov, candidato de ciencias biológicas<sup id="fnref:9" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:9" class="footnote" rel="footnote">9</a></sup>, sobre el aprendizaje de autómatas. Su autor participó en una conferencia científica dedicada a estos temas, que tuvo lugar en Karlsruhe (Alemania) en abril de 1961. El tema principal de la conferencia fue discutir las perspectivas para estudiar los principios del cerebro y crear nuevos tipos de máquinas cibernéticas sobre esta base. Se consideraron los problemas teóricos del aprendizaje, los mecanismos del cerebro que subyacen a la solución de problemas complejos del desarrollo de conceptos abstractos, reconocimiento de patrones, reconocimiento de voz y lectura de textos. Se discutieron las perspectivas de utilizar los principios del cerebro para crear nuevas máquinas cibernéticas. El artículo de A. V. Napalkov describe: también el trabajo que se lleva a cabo en la Universidad Estatal de Moscú.</p>

<p>La automatización de la gestión de procesos y sistemas complejos no libera completamente a una persona, sino que la pone en nuevas condiciones. Cuando una persona aprende a construir máquinas, cuya tarea es convertir un tipo de energía en otra, a menudo mecánica, se tiene un tipo de relación con la máquina, cuya acción y operación tiene que controlar. Los controles de la máquina, las herramienta y otros mecanismos deben estar dentro del rango de accesibilidad, y las acciones realizadas por la persona deben estar dentro de los límites de sus capacidades físicas y psicológicas. En la era de la automatización, surgieron nuevos problemas, ya que el hombre resultó ser uno de los eslabones de la nueva cadena máquina-control automático. Este objetivo es complicado cuando muchas máquinas, líneas de producción, talleres y fábricas se controlan automáticamente. No hay mecanismos y máquinas a prueba de fallas. Esta disposición se aplica igualmente a los órganos manuales y, aún más, a los órganos de control automático. Los fallos, aunque temporales, en el trabajo de cualquier eslabón (y en esta cadena no hay eslabones importantes y sin importancia) requieren una intervención inmediata en una serie de operaciones de control, y a menudo en tan poco tiempo que excede las capacidades fisiológicas y psicológicas de una persona. El problema de la fiabilidad surge nuevamente con toda su agudeza. Pero incluso con la acción “normal” del sistema, el papel del hombre sigue siendo decisivo, y las acciones que exceden sus capacidades deben ser excluidas.</p>

<p>Debe admitirse que esto a menudo está lejos de ser y no siempre se tiene en cuenta, y hay casos en que las organizaciones de diseño, diseñadores y tecnólogos se olvidan de la persona, creyendo sin ninguna razón que en la era de la automatización, el papel de una persona se vuelve auxiliar y su trabajo se facilita “automáticamente”… En el sistema máquina-autómata-humano, cada enlace, por separado y todo el sistema en su conjunto, debería funcionar en condiciones óptimas, y en particular esto se aplica a la carga física y psicofisiológica de una persona. En los últimos años, esta posición ha comenzado a ganar reconocimiento. Se presta considerable atención al desarrollo de la ciencia, que se llama psicotecnia. A veces se llama psicología de ingeniería.</p>

<p>Recordemos que en 1936 se publicó un decreto especial del Comité Central del Partido Comunista de Bolcheviques de toda la Unión el 4 de julio, <a href="https://ru.wikisource.org/wiki/%D0%9F%D0%BE%D1%81%D1%82%D0%B0%D0%BD%D0%BE%D0%B2%D0%BB%D0%B5%D0%BD%D0%B8%D0%B5_%D0%A6%D0%9A_%D0%92%D0%9A%D0%9F(%D0%B1)_%D0%BE%D1%82_4.07.1936_%D0%BE_%D0%BF%D0%B5%D0%B4%D0%BE%D0%BB%D0%BE%D0%B3%D0%B8%D1%87%D0%B5%D1%81%D0%BA%D0%B8%D1%85_%D0%B8%D0%B7%D0%B2%D1%80%D0%B0%D1%89%D0%B5%D0%BD%D0%B8%D1%8F%D1%85_%D0%B2_%D1%81%D0%B8%D1%81%D1%82%D0%B5%D0%BC%D0%B5_%D0%9D%D0%B0%D1%80%D0%BA%D0%BE%D0%BC%D0%BF%D1%80%D0%BE%D1%81%D0%BE%D0%B2" class="link-wikipedia">“Sobre las distorsiones paidológicas en el sistema del Comisariado Popular de Educación”</a>.<sup id="fnref:10" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:10" class="footnote" rel="footnote">10</a></sup> Esta decisión se dirigió contra errores ideológicos y metodológicos graves que se cometieron durante el examen del desarrollo mental y el talento de los escolares. Como resultado de estos errores, cada vez más niños se inscribieron en la categoría de retrasados ​​mentales, “defectuosos” y “difíciles” [sic]. Para corregir estos errores, el Comité Central del Partido Comunista de Bolcheviques de toda la Unión decidió: 1) restauración de pleno derecho de la pedagogía y los educadores; 2) eliminar el vínculo de los paidólogos con las escuelas y retirar los libros de texto paidológicos, etc. Esta solución eliminó toda una gama de errores cometidos en la pedagogía. Sin embargo, desafortunadamente, pronto resultó que algunos psicólogos entendieron esta instrucción del Comité Central del Partido Comunista de Bolcheviques de toda la Unión como una condena de toda la investigación sobre psicología del trabajo.</p>

<p>En la revista teórica y política del Comité Central del PCUS “Comunista”, nº 4 de 1956, es decir, 20 años después de la publicación de la resolución anterior, se publicó un editorial con el título titulado “Fortalecer la conexión de la ciencia psicológica con la práctica”. Confirmando la total inadmisibilidad de la repetición de errores antiguos y condenados en el campo de la psicología y la paidología, el artículo habló de la necesidad de estudiar y desarrollar los fundamentos científicos del desarrollo de la psique humana para estudiar las condiciones psicológicas para la organización efectiva de las actividades de las personas, especialmente su trabajo. Se trata de las enormes tareas que enfrentan los científicos en materia de un estudio amplio e integral de la psicología del trabajo, los factores psicológicos del aumento de la productividad laboral, el dominio de la tecnología avanzada y los métodos avanzados de trabajo, y el hecho de que el progreso tecnológico aumenta aún más la importancia y la eficacia de la aplicación de datos de la psicología del trabajo. Se recomienda asegurar la conexión directa entre la psicología y la práctica, organizar laboratorios psicológicos científico-prácticos en grandes empresas, en instituciones médicas, en la formación de mano de obra.</p>

<p>El artículo además establece claramente: “La psicología soviética parte del hecho de que la psique humana es un producto de su vida en sociedad, que sus características dependen de las condiciones históricas concretas de la actividad humana y que, por lo tanto, la psicología estudia la psique humana como un individuo público”. Por cierto, estas consideraciones deben recordarse al comparar las habilidades mentales de una persona y algunas operaciones lógicas realizadas por máquinas electrónicas.</p>

<p>Finalmente, este artículo dice: “No se puede guardar silencio sobre la actitud equivocada hacia la psicología extranjera. Algunos de nuestros científicos prestan poca atención incluso a los trabajos más serios de científicos extranjeros, sin someterlos a un análisis profundo, no tienen en cuenta lo positivo que aportan a la psicología, en particular, a la metodología de la investigación psicológica. Los intereses de la ciencia requieren urgentemente el estudio del estado de la ciencia psicológica en otros países, la lucha ideológica contra las tendencias reaccionarias, así como la consideración y el uso de lo positivo que existe: sin esto, el desarrollo exitoso de la ciencia es imposible “.</p>

<p>Aunque estas líneas se escribieron hace solo 5 años, la práctica cotidiana muestra que los pensamientos y direcciones interesantes contenidos en este artículo son completamente olvidados o generalmente desconocidos para algunos administradores de la industria.</p>

<p>En el artículo del prof. D. Yu. Panova y S. A. Oshanin en esta colección discuten las causas de la psicología de la ingeniería, el análisis de las capacidades humanas y de máquinas, la distribución de funciones entre una persona y una máquina, el análisis de la actividad del operador en sistemas de control complejos, la confiabilidad del operador humano en un sistema de control complejo, los problemas de capacitación y selección, y las tareas del laboratorio de psicología de la ingeniería industrial.</p>

<p>Una serie de preguntas en este artículo se plantean de una manera nueva. La literatura soviética sobre psicología de la ingeniería está limitada hasta ahora a unas pocas publicaciones: artículos. Esperemos que esto sea solo el comienzo. El descuido de esta ciencia afecta directamente las condiciones de trabajo de las empresas. Es altamente deseable que las personas que aún no entienden el significado de todo lo dicho anteriormente visiten algunas de nuestras plantas automatizadas; verían de primera mano lo importante que es estudiar las condiciones de trabajo en la era de la automatización.</p>

<h3 id="heading-iii-cibernética-en-humanidades">III. CIBERNÉTICA EN HUMANIDADES</h3>

<p>Ya en 1919, en el programa del segundo partido adoptado por el VIII Congreso del PCR, se decía: “Como principal y básico, determinando toda la política económica del gobierno soviético, establecer un aumento integral de las fuerzas productivas del país”. El XIV Congreso del Partido (1925) indicó que el plan leninista para la industrialización socialista del país se implementaría en el campo del desarrollo económico. Eso fue hace más de 35 años.</p>

<p>Ahora, en 1961, el borrador del Programa del PCUS dice: “La principal tarea económica del partido y del pueblo soviético es crear la base material y técnica del comunismo en dos décadas”. De acuerdo con esto, la ciencia económica tiene la tarea de generalizar nuevos fenómenos en la vida económica de la sociedad y desarrollar problemas económicos nacionales, cuya solución contribuye a la construcción exitosa del comunismo. “La atención de los economistas debe estar dirigida a encontrar formas de utilizar con mayor eficacia los recursos materiales y laborales en la economía nacional, los mejores métodos para planificar y organizar la producción preindustrial y agrícola, y desarrollar una distribución racional de las fuerzas productivas y los problemas técnicos y económicos de la construcción del comunismo”.</p>

<p>Vemos que a la ciencia económica se le ha asignado esencialmente la tarea de aumentar su eficacia, es decir, encontrar formas y medios para resolver los problemas más importantes en el campo de la economía indicados por la parte, con el menor gasto de tiempo, trabajo, materiales y energía. Hablando en la Conferencia de Científicos de toda la Unión el 14 de junio de 1961, A.N. Kosygin dijo:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Los medios técnicos modernos –me refiero a las computadoras de alta velocidad– también permiten mecanizar muchos procesos de trabajo mental en ila investigación científica, el diseño, la planificación de la economía nacional, en diversas operaciones contables y bancarias, en estadísticas, información provisional e incluso al traducir texto de un idioma a otro. También hay experiencia en la resolución con computadoras de muchos de los problemas económicos asociados con la planificación. Estos trabajos indican la gran eficiencia económica de la aplicación de métodos matemáticos y computadoras de alta velocidad. Es necesario ampliar la escala de aplicación práctica de estos métodos</p>
</blockquote>

<p>y sigue:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>En la ciencia económica y en la planificación basada en la investigación científica económica, es necesario avanzar más audaz y ampliamente hacia el uso de la tecnología de computación electrónica moderna y los métodos matemáticos. Los economistas y los matemáticos deberían desarrollar conjuntamente propuestas concretas para la aplicación de métodos matemáticos y tecnología informática moderna, máquinas de alta velocidad en investigación económica, planificación y gestión de la producción.</p>

  <p>Pravda, 15 de junio de 1961</p>
</blockquote>

<p>De estas declaraciones se deduce que el progreso de la ciencia económica depende en gran medida de su matematización. Pero para usar métodos matemáticos, primero debe tener información precisa. Los métodos existentes de contabilidad y procesamiento de la documentación primaria están diseñados para su promoción pausada. Existe una discrepancia en la metodología contable incluso en empresas que pertenecen a la misma rama de la economía y ubicadas en el territorio de una región administrativa. La mecanización de la contabilidad y la informática es extremadamente baja. En el transcurso de aproximadamente un año, Ekonomicheskaya Gazeta publicó una serie de discursos de trabajadores de contabilidad y estadística, abordando los problemas fundamentales de mejorar la contabilidad, las estadísticas y el análisis económico. Pero, como se señaló especialmente (Ekonomicheskaya Gazeta, nº 167, 16 de julio de 1961), las organizaciones y departamentos a los que se les pide que se preocupen por mejorar los métodos de contabilidad y las estadísticas no sacaron las conclusiones necesarias hasta julio de 1961. Recuerde que a fines de 1959, el Comité Central del PCUS y el Consejo de Ministros de la URSS adoptó una resolución especial sobre la mecanización de estas obras, y a principios de 1960 se celebró una reunión especial en Moscú para aumentar la eficiencia de la recopilación y el procesamiento de la documentación primaria.</p>

<p>Un artículo interesante publicado en Ekonomicheskaya Gazeta el 14 de diciembre de 1960, fue un artículo del ingeniero economista V. Mash [В. Маш], “Servicio de contabilidad y economía en las empresas estadounidenses”. Aunque los métodos y formas de organizar este servicio en los Estados Unidos no pueden ser aplicados de forma mecánica a las empresas soviéticas, indican que Estados Unidos está “haciendo grandes esfuerzos para lograr una gestión más flexible, clara y eficiente” con el fin de aumentar la eficiencia y la rentabilidad industrial producción</p>

<p>Por resolución del Presidium de la Academia de Ciencias de la URSS del 20 de mayo de 1960, se creó un Consejo Científico sobre la aplicación de métodos matemáticos en la investigación y planificación económica bajo la guía de acad. V.S. Nemchinova. Este consejo proporciona coordinación de trabajo en dos áreas principales:</p>

<ol>
  <li>la aplicación de métodos matemáticos y computadoras electrónicas en el análisis económico y la planificación en la escala de la economía nacional del país y las regiones económicas individuales;</li>
  <li>la aplicación de métodos matemáticos y computadoras electrónicas para resolver problemas técnicos y económicos.</li>
</ol>

<p>Las principales organizaciones en las que se basa el Consejo Científico son el Centro de Computación del Consejo Económico Estatal de la URSS, el Instituto de Ingeniería y Economía, las Universidades de Leningrado y Moscú y el Instituto de Matemáticas con el centro de cómputo de la Rama Siberiana de la Academia de Ciencias de la URSS, el Instituto de Trabajo y Salarios del Comité Estatal de Trabajo y Salarios, el Laboratorio de Métodos Económicos y Matemáticos de la Academia de Ciencias de la URSS.</p>

<p>La ciencia de administrar procesos y operaciones complejas, la cibernética, está encontrando una aplicación más amplia en la ciencia económica. El objetivo principal de la aplicación de la cibernética y las máquinas electrónicas en la economía socialista es la planificación económica. Ya hemos mencionado anteriormente que la preparación del plan debe basarse en suficiente volumen y contenido, información precisa y oportuna. Una economía socialista decidida permite el desarrollo de planes óptimos y más rentables. Eso le permite distribuir tareas entre empresas de tal manera que logre la máxima productividad general mientras observa las proporciones especificadas en la producción de diversos bienes. Se están realizando estudios sobre los esquemas óptimos para el transporte de cargas a granel de carbón, cemento, arena, etc.</p>

<p>La organización científica y la planificación de la economía nacional en la URSS y en los países de democracia popular abren las mayores posibilidades para la aplicación de métodos matemáticos y computadoras electrónicas. Pero esto no significa que la experiencia y los logros en este campo en el mundo capitalista deban ser descuidados.</p>

<p>Recientemente, se ha publicado material interesante sobre el trabajo en el campo de la metodología económica y matemática en algunos institutos en Francia (Ekonomicheskaya Gazeta, 23 de mayo de 1961). Allí, durante aproximadamente 2 años, ha habido una “Sociedad de Economía y Matemáticas Aplicadas” que aceptaba pedidos de grandes empresas para realizar cálculos económicos de la implementación más económica de varias operaciones comerciales. Se estudian y determinan las mejores opciones de transporte, asegurando la implementación del programa con un kilometraje total mínimo; se encuentran combinaciones racionales de suministro de combustible para complejos de producción, en los cuales se minimizan los costos totales; se determinan las rutas de tuberías más ventajosas, etc. Los autores de este artículo (V. Dadayan, A. Pokrovsky y Yu. Chernyak) recomiendan acertadamente tomar prestada esta experiencia organizando centros de cómputo en repúblicas sindicales o consejos económicos duales: el consejo económico y las academias republicanas de ciencias. Esto asegurará, según los autores, una combinación de resolución de problemas prácticos presentados por las necesidades de producción, con el desarrollo de los principios fundamentales de la metodología económica y matemática.</p>

<p>De considerable interés son los trabajos realizados en el Laboratorio Central de Investigación Mosoblsovnarkhoz para la Aplicación de Estadística Matemática y Tecnología de Computación Electrónica dirigido por el prof. A. M. Dlin.</p>

<p>En el artículo “Métodos matemáticos en la industria” (Ekonomicheskaya Gazeta, 21 de agosto de 1961, p. 18) el prof. A. M. Dlin y N. Pokrovsky hablan sobre su modelado matemático de procesos de producción individuales, el uso de programación lineal para determinar los tamaños de corte óptimos para chapa metálica, la expansión de la aplicación de estadísticas matemáticas en el control y análisis de producción, y la colaboración con el Laboratorio para la Aplicación de Matemática en métodos de investigación y planificación económica, liderados por Acad. V. S. Nemchinov.</p>

<p>Esta colección contiene un artículo de A. I. Kitov sobre el uso de la cibernética en la gestión de la economía nacional. Las consideraciones del autor sobre la planificación óptima y sobre la aplicación de métodos matemáticos en la planificación merecen una atención seria.</p>

<p>Es necesario destacar especialmente el maravilloso artículo del acad. S. L. Sobolev, “Para resolver problemas económicos con precisión matemática”, publicado en el Ekonomicheskaya Gazeta del 11 de junio de 1961.</p>

<p>Nuestra colección contiene un artículo sustancial del cand. de Ciencias Económicas V. D. Belkin “Cibernética y economía”. El autor enfatiza que bajo el socialismo es bastante posible crear un sistema automatizado integrado para administrar la economía del país, y esto tendrá un efecto mucho mayor que en los países capitalistas, que ya utilizan parcialmente la automatización en secciones separadas de la economía, pero que no pueden extender este método a la economía de todo el país.</p>

<p>En la colección “Problemas de cibernética” nº 5 (Fizmatgiz<sup id="fnref:11" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:11" class="footnote" rel="footnote">11</a></sup>) editada por A. A. Lyapunov, se colocan dos artículos de planificación muy importantes. El artículo de <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Julius_Anatolyevich_Schrader" class="link-wikipedia">Yu. A. Schreider</a>, “El problema de planificación dinámica y los autómatas”, es una generalización y desarrollo de la monografía de <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_E._Bellman" class="link-wikipedia">R. Bellman</a> sobre planificación dinámica, publicada en los Estados Unidos en 1957. Yu. A. Schreider describe un esquema que nos permite plantear el problema general de la planificación dinámica y derivar la principal ecuación funcional y establecer las propiedades básicas de sus soluciones. El artículo de E. G. Holshtein y D. B. Yudin, “Sobre una clase de problemas de planificación de la economía nacional”, contiene el desarrollo de algunos métodos especiales para resolver ciertos problemas importantes de programación lineal que permiten una reducción significativa en el trabajo computacional.</p>

<p>Nos detenemos en más detalles sobre la situación de la ciencia económica porque es especialmente importante. De hecho, al final, la única evaluación objetiva de todas nuestras acciones en el campo de la mecanización, la automatización, la expansión de la producción, la colocación de nuevos sitios de construcción, el uso de métodos de planificación más avanzados y todos nuestros esfuerzos para aumentar el ritmo del progreso científico y tecnológico es su eficiencia económica. No podemos permitirnos el lujo de no calcular con precisión en el campo de la economía. Al cumplir con las tareas de nuestro grupo establecidas en el nuevo programa, ya no podemos soportar el problema incompleto de fijación de precios, esta base de todos los cálculos económicos.</p>

<p>En su discurso en la Conferencia de científicos de toda la Unión en el Kremlin el 14 de junio de 1961, A.N. Kosygin dedicó una gran atención a los problemas económicos. Dijo:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>En las decisiones del XXI Congreso se afirmó que en el campo de las ciencias sociales, especialmente en la ciencia económica, la tarea es generalizar creativamente la experiencia de la construcción económica y cultural y estudiar las nuevas cuestiones que plantea la vida. La ciencia económica sigue estando a la zaga de las exigencias de la vida y la práctica, lo que fue señalado por el Comité Central del Partido y personalmente por el camarada Jruschov. Científicos-economistas: se presta poca atención al desarrollo de la metodología de planificación, la eficiencia de la inversión de capital, el uso racional de los activos fijos y otras cuestiones que plantea la práctica de la construcción económica.</p>

  <p>Pravda, 15 de junio de 1961</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Todos estos temas se plantean en cierta medida en artículos sobre el uso de la cibernética en la economía, que se colocan en la colección, y en artículos sobre los que llamamos especialmente la atención de los lectores.</p>

<p>Amamos y apreciamos los buenos libros de la literatura soviética y mundial. Se ha prestado mucha atención en los últimos años para mejorar el estudio de lenguas extranjeras. La lingüística, la ciencia del lenguaje, una de las ciencias más antiguas, es una disciplina descriptiva que, como parecía a lo largo de los años y hasta hace poco, estaba muy lejos de la tecnología y, especialmente, de las matemáticas. Pero la vida nos hace cambiar este punto de vista tradicional. En muchos países, los problemas de la traducción automática de un idioma a otro utilizando máquinas de información se han desarrollado con éxito. Esto requirió la creación de una nueva ciencia: la lingüística matemática o estructural.</p>

<p>Esta dirección de la lingüística es causada por la necesidad de un mejor uso de la enorme información científica publicada en muchos idiomas. La lingüística matemática es una ciencia completamente nueva, con solo unos 10 años. Pero en este corto período de tiempo se demostró que era aconsejable realizar la traducción automática, que era necesario desarrollar un solo idioma, un intermediario para la traducción de diferentes idiomas, que era aconsejable “enseñar” a la máquina electrónica a leer el discurso escrito y percibir las combinaciones de sonido de una voz humana. Estos problemas se están trabajando actualmente en nuestro país y en el extranjero.</p>

<p>El artículo de VV Ivanov y S. K. Shaumyan, “Problemas lingüísticos de cibernética y lingüística estructural”, publicado en nuestra colección, contiene muchas consideraciones muy interesantes y nuevas sobre estos temas. Habla sobre el papel del lenguaje en los procesos de control, la lingüística estructural como teoría abstracta del lenguaje y el significado teórico y aplicado de la lingüística aplicada.</p>

<p>Hay otra nueva área de aplicación de la cibernética en las humanidades, a saber, el campo del derecho. Parece que la cuestión del uso de las matemáticas, la automatización y la electrónica, y aún más la cibernética en la ciencia del derecho, no tiene una base real. Pero en el artículo de N. D. Andreev y D. A. Kerimov, “Las posibilidades de utilizar la técnica cibernética para resolver ciertos problemas legales”, se presentan una serie de consideraciones que demuestran lo contrario. Esta es una de las áreas de penetración de las ciencias exactas en el campo de las humanidades.</p>

<p>Se plantea la cuestión sobre la acumulación de información legal en máquinas lógicas y de información, sobre su sistematización y procesamiento, y sobre su emisión para el trabajo práctico en la elaboración de leyes y para aumentar la usabilidad de la legislación soviética. Se recomienda que las máquinas se utilicen para llevar a cabo diversas operaciones auxiliares intensivas en mano de obra relacionadas con la preparación de la codificación de la ley. Parece prometedor el uso de máquinas cibernéticas en la preparación de materiales para la generalización de la práctica judicial.</p>

<p>Finalmente, se propone utilizar máquinas para diversos tipos de examen documental.</p>

<p>Por supuesto, la aplicación práctica de estas ideas requerirá un trabajo preparatorio serio. Pero es interesante notar que la Universidad de Leningrado ya ha dado los primeros pasos en esta dirección.</p>

<p>Los delitos y la legislación existen en todo el mundo. Por lo tanto, es muy interesante estudiar la experiencia de aplicar los métodos anteriores en el extranjero. Ya hay literatura especial disponible sobre este tema. Se realizaron presentaciones sustantivas en el Simposio sobre la Mecanización de los Procesos de Pensamiento en Teddington en noviembre de 1958<sup id="fnref:12" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:12" class="footnote" rel="footnote">12</a></sup> y en la Conferencia Internacional sobre Lenguajes de Máquinas en septiembre de 1959 en los Estados Unidos<sup id="fnref:13" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:13" class="footnote" rel="footnote">13</a></sup>.</p>

<p>Esperamos que el artículo sobre el uso de métodos y herramientas cibernéticos en la ley atraiga la atención de nuestros abogados.</p>

<h3 id="heading-iv-cibernética-en-ciencia-y-tecnología">IV. CIBERNÉTICA EN CIENCIA Y TECNOLOGÍA</h3>

<p>El borrador del Programa del PCUS planteó el requisito de desarrollar métodos para influir en las condiciones climáticas. Este es un viejo sueño de la humanidad, completamente irrealizable en el pasado. La implementación de esta tarea en el futuro cercano es una tarea extremadamente difícil, pero las posibilidades modernas de la ciencia ya permiten ponerla en práctica.</p>

<p>Aparentemente, deberíamos comenzar mejorando los métodos de predicción del clima. En este sentido, se ha hecho mucho en las últimas décadas. Se proporciona una ayuda significativa mediante medios e instrumentos más avanzados para recopilar y procesar información sobre el estado y la dinámica de la atmósfera. Pero la introducción de métodos científicos matemáticos y máquinas electrónicas en el servicio de predicción meteorológica ha comenzado, y esto ya da un resultado indudablemente positivo.</p>

<p>Es mucho más difícil influir en los factores que determinan el clima. Esta es una tarea de control típica, es decir, el impacto en grandes reservas de materia y energía con la ayuda de cantidades mucho más pequeñas, pero el impacto es en aquellos factores que determinan el estado del sistema. Los técnicos de radio son conscientes de la eficacia con la que el voltaje en la red de control de una lámpara electrónica actúa sobre el consumo de energía de la fuente de alimentación del circuito anódico y sobre la aparición de un voltaje mucho mayor en el circuito anódico en el modo de amplificación de voltaje. Este es un efecto de retransmisión bien conocido en la técnica. En esencia, toda la electrónica se basa en la gestión de pequeños potenciales, grandes reservas de energía y la conversión de esta energía en la forma deseada.</p>

<p>Usando este principio, podemos dispersar nubes y nebulosas para un mejor uso de la energía solar, cuando se desee, o, por el contrario, condensar la humedad en las nubes y causar lluvia artificial o niebla. La solución de estos problemas hoy en pequeña escala ya es posible y se está implementando.</p>

<p>Por supuesto, es mucho más difícil influir en el clima. Pero, ¿no está sucediendo ahora un riego a gran escala de desiertos y drenaje de pantanos? ¿Es imposible conducir la silvicultura a una escala mucho mayor y mucho más racional? ¿Soportaremos nosotros y nuestra descendencia el hecho de que las vastas extensiones de nuestra patria están cubiertas de permafrost “eterno”? Una gran cantidad de energía solar inagotable cae a la Tierra y, sin duda, llegará el momento en que aprenderemos cómo usarla mejor. ¿Usamos la energía eólica en alguna escala notable? Todos estos son problemas de gran política económica y estrategia, pero pueden resolverse ahora. Esto también incluye la tarea de cambiar el curso de los ríos y la dirección de sus aguas hacia donde el agua no es suficiente.</p>

<p>Por supuesto, la solución de estos problemas requiere coraje, audacia e investigación profunda. Pero el partido no plantea tareas fáciles para los científicos soviéticos. Esta es la gran ventaja de la gestión socialista de la economía nacional: solo le permite buscar y encuentrar soluciones óptimas para tareas y problemas difíciles pero importantes.</p>

<p>La matemática electrónica y la cibernética pueden proporcionar excelentes servicios en el campo del cambio climático, pero bajo una condición: las tareas deben plantearse a gran escala y las fuerzas necesarias deben concentrarse en resolverlas.</p>

<p>Esta colección contiene un artículo de S. A. Mashkovich “Cibernética y meteorología”, que desarrolla ideas sobre la posibilidad de predecir mejor el clima, el efecto sobre el clima y el impacto sobre el clima.</p>

<p>Una de las industrias de más rápido crecimiento en la Unión Soviética es la industria química. En el Pleno de mayo del Comité Central del PCUS (1958), se prestó especial atención a esta industria. En los 3 años que han pasado desde entonces, la situación en la química ha cambiado radicalmente. Se encargaron más de 60 empresas industriales; muchas capacidades se pondrán en servicio en 1961.</p>

<p>La ciencia y la industria química se están desarrollando rápidamente en todo el mundo. Al mismo tiempo, el uso de altas presiones y temperaturas, altas tasas de reacción y muchos procesos tecnológicos nocivos e inaccesibles crean una necesidad urgente de mecanización y automatización de la industria química. La especial complejidad de muchos procesos abre posibilidades para la aplicación de métodos modernos de cibernética en el control. Los principales requisitos en este caso son, obviamente, la optimización de los procesos tecnológicos y la garantía de un alto grado de fiabilidad (seguridad) de funcionamiento tanto del propio equipo químico como de los medios de automatización electrónica (o neumática) utilizados para controlarlo. La aplicación de las matemáticas, la estadística matemática, la teoría de la probabilidad, la lógica matemática y otras secciones de las matemáticas para la descripción estricta de las regularidades que actúan en la producción química caracteriza un lado’ de la materia. El segundo lado es el trabajo informativo sobre la literatura química. Esta misma parte del trabajo está dedicada principalmente al artículo de G. E. Vladuts.</p>

<p>El autor señala que en la actualidad, la literatura química representa aproximadamente un tercio de toda la literatura científica impresa hasta el momento. Es imposible sistematizar y encontrar la información necesaria utilizando métodos antiguos, ya que esto absorberá demasiado tiempo. Por lo tanto, en la actualidad, los especialistas de todos los perfiles están extremadamente interesados en automatizar las búsquedas de información utilizando máquinas especiales de información y lógica.</p>

<p>Un problema relacionado es la creación de un lenguaje de máquina de información: un lenguaje para la química, es decir, la traducción del lenguaje conocido de fórmulas estructurales de compuestos químicos en una secuencia lineal de caracteres. Este problema puede resolverse con máquinas especiales, que procesan el lenguaje químico ordinario en máquinas “comprensibles” y un lenguaje químico de máquina conveniente. Aquí se abren interesantes posibilidades para asignar a las máquinas lógicas de información las funciones de “pensamiento químico”, es decir, la solución del problema de la elección del modo óptimo de síntesis de algún compuesto químico aún no descrito. Tales máquinas en el futuro serán de “auto-aprendizaje”. Todo esto facilitará muchas veces el trabajo de los científicos e investigadores en química.</p>

<p>Un artículo de G. E. Vladets sin duda ampliará los horizontes de los lectores que no se dedican a estudiar las posibilidades de las máquinas de lógica de la información en química.</p>

<p>¿Cuánto ha madurado la necesidad de lidiar con la aplicación de las matemáticas, la automatización y la cibernética en la química en un grado mucho mayor de lo que se hace ahora? Uno puede juzgar por la enorme atención prestada a estos problemas en el extranjero. La química se caracteriza por la existencia de dos áreas de uso de la cibernética: el efecto de control de la información sobre los procesos químicos en la producción con el propósito de su optimización y las actividades de tecnología de la información en el mundo de la literatura química, científica, técnica, de patentes, etc.</p>

<p>Se realizó una reunión interesante sobre algunos de estos temas en el Club de Negocios del Ekonomicheskaya Gazeta, cuyos materiales fueron publicados en el periódico del 4 de septiembre de 1961</p>

<p>Junto con la compleja mecanización y automatización de la industria, un nuevo campo de automatización, la teleautomática, se ha extendido en los últimos años. Se está realizando un trabajo interesante en esta área bajo la dirección de V. A. Ilyin. En el artículo “Teleautomática y cibernética”, el autor habla sobre el desarrollo de métodos y herramientas de telemecánica para la recopilación remota de información, señalización, regulación y control en relación con objetos dispersos. Naturalmente, en dichos sistemas se requiere garantizar una alta confiabilidad, un funcionamiento sin problemas de todos los dispositivos y medios para recopilar, procesar información y emitir comandos. Por medio de la teleautomática, muchas instalaciones de los sistemas de energía del país ya están equipadas. Aparentemente, se presta la mayor atención al trabajo realizado con éxito durante varios años en la telemecanización masiva de campos petroleros. De considerable interés es también un sistema integrado de automatización y telemecanización en el campo del riego. Cuando hay muchos objetos de administración, puede ser necesario recopilar y procesar información y administración extensas en el modo óptimo. Las máquinas electrónicas pueden ayudar. Por lo tanto, las tareas de automatización remota se acercan a las tareas que se resuelven mediante la cibernética.</p>

<p>De considerable interés es el folleto de V. A. Ilyin “Sistemas de telemecánica para objetos dispersos” (Gosenergoizdat, 1960).</p>

<p>Según la información recibida del autor, el trabajo en el campo de la telemecanización de los pozos petroleros ha avanzado tanto con nosotros que ya más del 20% de ellos están telemecanizados.</p>

<p>Cabe señalar el gran interés mostrado en el primer congreso internacional sobre control automático (Moscú, 1960) en temas de recolección remota de información, telemetría, su confiabilidad, inmunidad al ruido y eficiencia.</p>

<p>“La electrificación, que es el núcleo de la construcción de la economía de la sociedad comunista, desempeña un papel de liderazgo en el desarrollo de todos los sectores de la economía nacional, asegurando todo el progreso tecnológico moderno. Por lo tanto, es necesario garantizar un ritmo más rápido de producción de electricidad”. Dicha evaluación se da en el borrador del Programa de electrificación de PCUS del país.</p>

<p>Hace más de 40 años, en 1920, se desarrolló el primer plan maestro para el desarrollo de la economía nacional de la Rusia soviética, que sigue siendo de gran importancia como ejemplo de un prometedor plan económico nacional estatal. En el VIII Congreso de los Soviets de toda Rusia en diciembre de 1920, Vladimir Ilich Lenin describió el plan para la electrificación de Rusia, que fue revisado por la Comisión Estatal por la Electrificación de Rusia (<a href="https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/GOELRO" class="link-wikipedia">GOELRO</a>), como el segundo programa del partido, como un gran plan económico que indica la forma de transferir a la Rusia atrasada a una nueva base económica, necesaria para la construcción del comunismo. “Tal base”, dijo Vladimir Ilich, “es solo electricidad. El comunismo es el poder soviético más la electrificación de todo el país” (obras completas<sup id="fnref:1:2" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>, 4ª ed., vol. 31, p. 486).</p>

<p>El valor para establecer metas para el plan GOELRO solo puede evaluarse si tenemos en cuenta la situación en el país en 1919-1920. Si en 1913 se generaron alrededor de 1.9-2.0 miles de millones de kWh de electricidad en Rusia, entonces en 1920 se generó 4 veces menos, alrededor de 0.5 miles de millones de kWh. Al mismo tiempo en los EE. UU. se generaron 50×10<sup>9</sup> kWh, es decir, 100 veces más. Después de 40 años, la imagen cambió dramáticamente. En 1960, se produjeron 292×10<sup>9</sup> en la URSS y alrededor de 900×10<sup>9</sup> kWh (en las terminales de las centrales eléctricas) en los Estados Unidos, es decir, “solo” 3 veces más. Pero si no hubiera habido la Segunda Guerra Mundial, que no solo se detuvo, sino que también retrasó el desarrollo de la electrificación de la URSS y no hizo daño a los Estados Unidos, entonces habríamos generado del 40 al 50% de la capacidad de generación de electricidad en los EE. UU en 1960.</p>

<p>De acuerdo con las tareas del proyecto de Programa del PCUS, en 1970 la URSS producirá entre 900 y 1.000 y en 1980 entre 2.700 y 3.000 miles de millones de kWh de electricidad. Esto significa triplicar aproximadamente la generación de electricidad cada 10 años. En los Estados Unidos, hubo aproximadamente una duplicación por cada 10 años, y si se puede hablar de suposiciones (en lugar de planes), estas tasas continuarán en los Estados Unidos durante los próximos 20 años (ver la revista “Planovoye khozyaystvo”<sup id="fnref:14" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:14" class="footnote" rel="footnote">14</a></sup>, 1961, nº 7, p. 84). Si esto se cumple, en 1980 en la URSS y los EE. UU. se generará aproximadamente la misma cantidad de electricidad.</p>

<p>Este libro se centra en los problemas y desafíos de la gestión de sistemas complejos. Hemos dado cifras sobre el crecimiento de la generación de electricidad para mostrar los retos que habrá que afrontar para gestionar las enormes reservas de energía del futuro de la manera más ventajosa y óptima.</p>

<p>En los últimos años, se ha prestado mucha atención a los problemas de automatización de la gestión de plantas de energía individuales, y aquí se han logrado resultados significativos. Las tareas de control automático de sistemas de energía separados, más o menos grandes, se han resuelto con éxito y continúan realizándose. Nos acercamos a la tarea más importante de una gestión conjunta de la distribución del Sistema Unificado de Energía de la parte europea de la URSS. En un futuro próximo, el problema de un sistema energético unificado de toda la Unión Soviética comenzará a resolverse y, de acuerdo con esto, el problema de su gestión óptima. Finalmente, la tarea de unir los sistemas energéticos nacionales de los países de la democracia popular y la URSS en un solo sistema energético ya se está estudiando. Naturalmente, el problema surgirá de la gestión óptima y confiable de sistemas tan complejos, y este es un problema típico de la cibernética, y es necesario prepararse para una fiesta científica ahora.</p>

<p>En mayo de 1960 se celebró en Kiev una reunión científica y técnica sobre la aplicación de la tecnología informática en el diseño y el funcionamiento de los sistemas de energía. En la reunión se adoptó una decisión detallada en la que se señaló que para la investigación científica y para la práctica de la ingeniería en el ámbito del diseño y el funcionamiento de los sistemas de energía es necesario utilizar ampliamente métodos matemáticos relativamente complejos que atraigan la teoría de la probabilidad, la teoría cualitativa y los métodos numéricos para resolver ecuaciones diferenciales lineales y no lineales, el álgebra superior, etc. En la reunión se señaló que esos problemas sólo pueden resolverse con la ayuda de la moderna tecnología informática, para cuya aplicación se definieron las siguientes orientaciones principales en el sector de la energía:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Perspectiva y planificación continua, procesamiento de materiales estadísticos e informativos relevantes.</li>
  <li>Diseño de plantas de energía, redes eléctricas, transmisión de energía a larga distancia, dispositivos de automatización; trabajos de investigación.</li>
  <li>Cálculos del modo de operación (planificado y operativo), análisis de los modos de control de accidentes del sistema y el equipo, registro y procesamiento de la información primaria.</li>
  <li>Control automático de los regímenes de sistemas de energía, plantas de energía y otras instalaciones de energía.</li>
</ol>

<p>Por último, recordamos que en el I Congreso de la Federación Internacional de Por último, cabe recordar que en el I Congreso de la Federación Internacional de Control Automático (IFAC), celebrado en 1960 en Moscú, representantes de la URSS, los Estados Unidos, Inglaterra, Italia, Polonia, Checoslovaquia, Hungría y otros países presentaron interesantes ponencias sobre la automatización del control de los sistemas de energía y la utilización de dispositivos electrónicos de computación con ese fin.</p>

<p>Todas estas consideraciones fueron la base de un interesante artículo “Cibernética y Sistemas de Potencia” del prof. Venikov, ganador del Premio Lenin.</p>

<p>El borrador del Programa establece: “El crecimiento de la economía nacional requerirá un desarrollo acelerado de todos los medios de transporte. Las tareas más importantes en la esfera del transporte son: la expansión del transporte y la construcción de carreteras y la garantía de la plena satisfacción de las necesidades de la economía nacional y de la población en todos los tipos de transporte; un mayor reequipamiento técnico de los ferrocarriles y otros medios de transporte; un aumento significativo de la velocidad de los ferrocarriles y de las rutas marítimas y fluviales; el desarrollo coordinado de todos los tipos de transporte como componentes de una red de transporte única. La proporción de transporte por oleoducto aumentará”.</p>

<p>Si tenemos en cuenta el tamaño del territorio de la URSS, el rápido desarrollo de la industria y la agricultura en todo el país, el desarrollo de nuevas zonas para la extracción de minerales, la necesidad de agilizar el transporte y garantizar su seguridad y viabilidad económica, no es difícil comprender que el problema del transporte no puede resolverse con los métodos antiguos.</p>

<p>La colección contiene el artículo de I. Ya. Aksenov “Problemas de transporte de la cibernética”, cuyo autor dice que el transporte más que muchos otros sectores de la economía necesita la introducción más urgente y rápida de la cibernética, tanto por sus características debido a la naturaleza del propio transporte, como por los importantes resultados técnicos y económicos que puede proporcionar tanto en el transporte como en el Estado en su conjunto. Lo mismo se afirma en el artículo del Ministro de Ferrocarriles de la URSS B. Beshchev en “Pravda” de agosto de 1961 con respecto al transporte ferroviario: “El control del tráfico de trenes y todos los procesos de formación y desestabilización de los trenes en las estaciones se llevarán a cabo utilizando dispositivos cibernéticos”.</p>

<p>Ya hemos mencionado anteriormente que la cibernética estudia los sistemas dinámicos complejos y los procesos que tienen lugar en ellos. El transporte es un ejemplo típico de un sistema dinámico gigante y altamente complejo que es difícil de controlar para lograr el máximo efecto con el mínimo costo.</p>

<p>Al mismo tiempo, los medios técnicos de reunión y tratamiento de la información para la solución de este problema prácticamente sólo empiezan a aparecer. Es necesario señalar la iniciativa de los ciudadanos de Kiev que celebran en 1961 y 1962 el seminario por correspondencia “Cibernética en el transporte”. Los organizadores del seminario señalan que la aplicación de los progresos técnicos en el transporte plantea una serie de tareas sobre la automatización del control del tráfico, la introducción de dispositivos cibernéticos y de computadoras electrónicas automáticas en la práctica de la producción del transporte. Dado que el transporte es una rama de la economía nacional con una gestión centralizada y que utiliza los mismos métodos para encontrar soluciones óptimas, podemos esperar que el uso de máquinas de control especializadas, métodos matemáticos de resolución de problemas multivariantes y sistemas de control automatizados tenga un gran efecto económico.</p>

<p>De considerable interés es el trabajo de nuestros institutos de transporte ferroviario en el desarrollo de un centro de computación especial, llevado a cabo bajo la dirección del miembro correspondiente de la Academia de Ciencias de la URSS, el prof. A. P. Petrov. También merece atención seria el trabajo de B. Del Rio, N. A. Samarin y L. V. Safris sobre el uso de máquinas digitales electrónicas para la elaboración de horarios de trenes paralelos, realizado por el Instituto de Ingenieros de Hierro: Transporte por carretera en Rostov del Don.</p>

<h3 id="heading-v-algunos-resultados">V. ALGUNOS RESULTADOS</h3>

<p>Hemos hablado del proceso de las matemáticas de muchas ciencias típicas de nuestra época: biología, medicina, economía, lingüística, meteorología, química y otras. En todos los casos se pasa de la descripción, de las evaluaciones cualitativas generales al establecimiento de regularidades matemáticas exactas. El propósito de esta evolución de las ciencias naturales y humanas, dirigida conscientemente por el hombre, es una penetración más profunda en la esencia de los fenómenos del mundo exterior que nos rodea, de la naturaleza viva y especialmente de nuestro organismo. La principal tarea de esta actividad es el uso de las regularidades cognitivas para satisfacer las necesidades humanas. No podemos cambiar las leyes naturales de la naturaleza, pero podemos, habiéndolas aprendido, aprender a controlarlas.</p>

<p>Así surgió, respondiendo a una necesidad consciente, una nueva ciencia de gestión: la cibernética. Decimos la “nueva” ciencia de la gestión porque esta ciencia no gestiona procesos simples y ordinarios. En la gran mayoría de los casos, en la práctica, uno tiene que lidiar con relaciones confiables de causa y efecto e interacciones simples, cuando el control se reduce a equipos elementales, cuyo resultado se conoce de antemano de manera confiable. En estas condiciones más comunes de práctica y vida cotidiana, la cibernética es completamente innecesaria. La necesidad de desarrollar una nueva ciencia de gestión surge en aquellos casos complejos cuando los viejos métodos aplicados a casos simples dejan de funcionar. La cibernética brinda la oportunidad de administrar sistemas complejos, operaciones complejas realizadas por equipos humanos, procesos de producción complejos, procesos infinitamente complejos que ocurren en la naturaleza viva.</p>

<p>La cibernética estudia formaciones complejas, un estado de muchos elementos estructurales interconectados organizados en un solo sistema. Los elementos compuestos realizan sus funciones inherentes.</p>

<p>El estado de un sistema está determinado por los valores de los parámetros, variables o coordenadas de sus elementos constitutivos y sus derivados. Los valores de las variables pueden variar en el tiempo y el espacio. Entonces el sistema también cambia su estado y se vuelve dinámico. Si las derivadas de las variables son cero, el sistema dinámico pasa al estado de reposo y se vuelve estático. Al afectar las variables de un sistema dinámico o sus derivados, el sistema se mueve de un estado a otro, un nuevo estado. La transición del sistema de un estado a otro se denomina comúnmente proceso. La transferencia de un sistema a un nuevo estado mediante la influencia de sus variables — esto es el control.</p>

<p>Por lo tanto, la cibernética estudia los procesos que ocurren en sistemas dinámicos complejos cuando son controlados. Si el control lo lleva a cabo una persona o mecanismos, así como máquinas que funcionan de acuerdo con un programa establecido por una persona, entonces es útil. El propósito de la administración en este caso es transferir el sistema a un nuevo estado preasignado. La cibernética también estudia los procesos de control que ocurren en la naturaleza que nos rodea, así como los procesos de control más complejos en los organismos vivos. La cibernética finalmente estudia los procesos sociales y las operaciones realizadas por colectivos humanos.</p>

<p>El complejo proceso de gestión se divide en operaciones de gestión individuales realizadas en una secuencia determinada o en una combinación determinada. Tales, por ejemplo, operaciones de producción industrial. Pero incluso en la sociedad humana, ciertas personas o grupos organizados de personas llevan a cabo ciertas acciones u operaciones con propósito que están subordinadas a un determinado plan. Existen muchas acciones u operaciones de este tipo: son operaciones de crédito, transporte, seguros, operaciones militares, etc. Pueden ser simples y complejas, independientes entre sí o interconectadas.</p>

<p>Desde el punto de vista de la cibernética los sistemas dinámicos complejos en la naturaleza viva, en la industria y en la sociedad humana son sistemas controlados, objetos de control. Por eso, antes de comenzar a controlar, es necesario estudiar en detalle o, como se dice en el lenguaje científico moderno, recoger información, caracterizando el sistema a controlar, estudiar esta información y revelar aquellos rasgos, que es necesario conocer para la realización del control: estructura, organización, conexiones mutuas y funciones de los elementos. Los resultados de este estudio DEBEN expresarse en lenguaje matemático y lógico-matemático.</p>

<p>Si el sistema controlado se estudia y describe matemáticamente, es necesario crear un sistema de control para influir en las variables del sistema controlado según los objetivos y las tareas establecidas. Es fundamentalmente completamente indiferente que el sistema controlado se controle automáticamente o mediante una cierta combinación de comandos. En general se supone que todos los dispositivos cibernéticos funcionan automáticamente utilizando principios de retroalimentación. En muchos casos esto es cierto. Pero también hay casos en los que se introducen conscientemente retrasos entre los pasos individuales o las etapas de control. Por ejemplo, el proceso de reunión de información puede separarse, incluso a intervalos prolongados, del proceso de aplicación de esa información para la gestión.</p>

<p>Si nos adhierimos a la terminología aceptada y la hace más clara para los expertos, en particular para los técnicos de radio, el sistema operado es una “carga” para el sistema de control. Los comandos de control programados y codificados se dan a la entrada del sistema de control (por ejemplo, la máquina de control electrónico). Estos comandos son “comprensibles” para el dispositivo o sistema de control. Pero esto no significa que sean “comprensibles” para el sistema controlado. Deben ser procesados en consecuencia para que los comandos de control provenientes del sistema de control sean ejecutados correctamente por el sistema controlado. Un buen ejemplo es el sistema telefónico automático. Llamando al abonado correcto marcando un número de teléfono conocido, envían el comando de control a la central telefónica. Allí se procesa el comando y se busca el número del suscriptor. Si la línea está libre y el número de teléfono del abonado no está ocupado, la llamada se realiza y el abonado se conecta al dispositivo. La estación, el abonado o la línea ocupada se reconoce por los pitidos – señales de retroalimentación de información. Así pues, una central telefónica automática de distrito, junto con las líneas de comunicación y los abonados, es un buen ejemplo de un sistema dinámico complejo controlado por muchos dispositivos o sistemas de control más sencillos. Como cualquier sistema dinámico complejo, tiene sus propias características. Una de sus características es el cambio de los puntos de origen y la información percibida, es decir, los sujetos y objetos: la gestión.</p>

<p>Otro ejemplo es el sistema de control remoto. Aquí, las funciones de los Otro ejemplo es el sistema de control remoto. Aquí, las funciones de los sistemas de control y gestión están distribuidas de forma clara e inequívoca. Los puntos de desarrollo y emisión de comandos de control y los objetos de control o sistemas controlados pueden ser separados por “largas distancias”. El entorno intermedio puede ser muy diferente: la atmósfera de la Tierra, el espacio exterior o el agua. Los enlaces de información de retroalimentación pueden existir y actuar automáticamente, pero también pueden estar ausentes si las relaciones causa-efecto se conocen de manera precisa y confiable y la ejecución de comandos no está en duda. Por lo general, se utilizan enlaces de información de retroalimentación automática, pero este no es el único esquema posible.</p>

<p>El control remoto de los sistemas de energía puede servir como otro ejemplo de la existencia separada de sistemas de control y controlados.</p>

<p>Nos centramos en estos ejemplos y en la terminología, porque en la mayoría de los casos el término sistema de “control” se utiliza en la literatura cibernética en un sentido ligeramente distinto: significa un conjunto de dispositivos que emiten y procesan órdenes y sistemas que las perciben. Esto tiene la justificación de que a veces es difícil separar el sistema de control del sistema controlado en nuestra terminología. Los organismos vivos pueden servir de ejemplo en este caso. La fuente de información inicial suele ser éste o aquel proceso que tiene lugar en el entorno externo. Si un organismo tiene receptores de esta fuente de información, reacciona a ellos. A través de muchos canales del sistema nervioso (y el cuerpo escoge las formas más ventajosas y confiables) la señal de irritación se transmite y se procesa repetidamente en el camino hacia el cerebro. Después de un procesamiento muy complejo de la información que ha llegado aquí se producen señales de respuesta que se transmiten a los órganos ejecutivos, que en última instancia llevan a cabo la respuesta del cuerpo a la irritación externa. Aquí las funciones de los comandos o las señales para controlar su procesamiento y ejecución están continua y repetidamente entrelazadas, y cada señal de comando subsiguiente está determinada por la información recibida a través de los canales de retroalimentación. Todos estos procesos son mucho más complicados que en la tecnología y la vida social. El estudio de estos procesos acaba de comenzar, pero está progresando bien en nuestro país y en muchos otros. Este estudio es una fuente inagotable para enriquecer nuestro conocimiento e imitarlo en casos de control más sencillos.</p>

<p>Sin embargo, cada acto elemental de este complejo proceso se ajusta a nuestra terminología. En cuanto a la gestión de mecanismos, máquinas, aparatos, operaciones de colectivos humanos, nos parece que en este caso nuestra terminología es bastante aplicable.</p>

<p>No hay artículos sobre máquinas matemáticas electrónicas en nuestra colección. Sobre esta cuestión hay una extensa literatura científica y popular. Desde las posiciones de la cibernética las máquinas electrónicas son medios modernos de la cibernética técnica. En las máquinas electrónicas del segundo volumen se mencionarán los problemas de su desarrollo ulterior, en particular la reducción de sus tamaños, la miniaturización de los elementos estructurales y, sobre todo, los problemas de aumento de su fiabilidad operacional y de aumento de la velocidad.</p>

<p>En esta colección tampoco se tratan cuestiones de fiabilidad. Este tema se tratará a fondo en el volumen 2 de la colección. Consideramos que este tema es uno de los más importantes. Debemos admitir que la situación en esta zona es obviamente desfavorable. La fiabilidad de la automática electrónica no satisface a nadie. Sólo se puede hablar de una amplia introducción de estos medios en la economía nacional si se resuelve satisfactoriamente el problema de la fiabilidad. No debería haber ilusiones. Pero al mismo tiempo es necesario reconocer que el problema del aumento de la fiabilidad de los medios de la automática electrónica y la cibernética no puede ser resuelto por los esfuerzos de algunos expertos en electrónica. Es necesario involucrar más ampliamente a los matemáticos, diseñadores y tecnólogos en su decisión. Es totalmente injustificado pensar que la fiabilidad de los dispositivos y sensores primarios es bastante alta. Igualmente equivocado: la opinión de la alta fiabilidad de los mecanismos ejecutivos. Esto se aplica principalmente a la industria química.</p>

<p>Los intentos de “dejar de lado” el problema de la fiabilidad como un problema ficticio que supuestamente no existe no resisten ninguna crítica. Se debe establecer una responsabilidad estricta por encubrir y desatender estas cuestiones. Esto comienza a ser entendido por la mayoría de las personas progresistas responsables del progreso científico y tecnológico. Pero hay que recordar que el problema de la fiabilidad, aun si hubiera sido resuelto satisfactoriamente hoy (que por supuesto no lo es), se plantea de nuevo mañana y nunca será eliminado mientras exista el desarrollo e introducción de nuevas tecnologías y nuevos dispositivos. Este es un problema “eterno”, y nunca será resuelto por eventos episódicos.</p>

<h3 id="heading-vi-conclusión">VI. CONCLUSIÓN</h3>

<p>Hace tiempo que estamos acostumbrados a confiar firmemente en la ayuda de nuestra comunidad en todos los casos difíciles. Somos conscientes de que la ciencia se desarrolla solo como resultado del trabajo creativo persistente y decidido de científicos individuales y en laboratorios bien organizados y equipados con instrumentos y equipos científicos modernos.</p>

<p>Desde los primeros días del poder soviético, V.I. Lenin, un científico brillante y un organizador maravilloso, ayudó al desarrollo de la ciencia joven soviética y la dirigió a resolver los problemas económicos más importantes. No todos recuerdan que, por iniciativa de V.I. Lenin, el programa del partido adoptado en el VIII Congreso en 1919 establece:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>El gobierno soviético ya ha tomado una serie de medidas destinadas al desarrollo de la ciencia y su acercamiento a la producción: la creación de una red completa de nuevos institutos científicos y aplicados, laboratorios, estaciones de prueba, plantas piloto para probar nuevos métodos técnicos, mejoras e invenciones, contabilidad y organización. Todas las fuerzas y medios científicos, etc., el PCR, apoyando todas estas medidas, busca desarrollarlas más y crear las condiciones más favorables para el trabajo científico en relación con el aumento de las fuerzas productivas del país.</p>

  <p>Resoluciones y decisiones del PCUS, parte I, ed. VII, 1953, pp. 423-424</p>
</blockquote>

<p>¿Algún otro país tuvo que experimentar las dificultades que recayeron sobre la ciencia soviética durante los años de bloqueo, hambruna e intervención? ¿Han tenido que evacuar otros países no solo una gran cantidad de empresas industriales, sino casi todas las instituciones de educación superior, como era necesario hacer en Leningrado y en muchas otras ciudades que fueron objeto de una invasión fascista en la Segunda Guerra Mundial? Los científicos de otros países nunca han experimentado esto. Sin embargo, unos años después del final de la guerra, la primera planta de energía nuclear comenzó a funcionar en la Unión Soviética, y poco después se lanzaron los primeros satélites, y hoy, los primeros astronautas en volar alrededor de la Tierra.</p>

<p>Estos éxitos son aún más notables porque se han logrado, a pesar de las dificultades más recientes experimentadas en un país que se consideraba atrasado entre 30 y 40 años atrás.</p>

<p>Es interesante notar que, según la UNESCO, en los últimos 50 años, el aumento anual promedio en el número de científicos en el mundo ha alcanzado el 7% con un crecimiento de la población mucho más bajo (aproximadamente 1,7% por año). Esto significa que el número de científicos en el mundo se duplica cada 10 años, mientras que la población mundial se duplica en 40 años. Para resolver las tareas establecidas para la ciencia soviética durante los próximos 20 años, es necesario capacitar a un gran número de jóvenes científicos, expandir significativamente la base de investigación, atraer a las universidades a la investigación a una escala mucho mayor de lo que se está haciendo actualmente, destacar las áreas más importantes de investigación y centrarse en ellos las principales fuerzas. El equipamiento de las universidades, laboratorios de institutos y fábricas debería alinearse con la complejidad de resolver nuevos problemas científicos. Se debe prestar especial atención al desarrollo de la instrumentación, en particular la instrumentación científica y el equipo necesario para realizar trabajos experimentales.</p>

<p>Todas estas tareas fueron discutidas en la Conferencia de Trabajadores Científicos de toda la Unión y en una reunión de trabajadores de escuelas superiores en el Kremlin en el verano de 1961. La validez del tema y los requisitos para el equipo científico de los laboratorios de investigación y educación depende de los trabajadores científicos y los profesores universitarios.</p>

<p>Se debe prestar especial atención al desarrollo de la teoría y los principios para la creación de nuevas máquinas, sistemas automáticos y telemecánicos, el desarrollo intensivo de la radioelectrónica, el desarrollo de fundamentos teóricos y la mejora técnica de las computadoras, el control y las máquinas de información, como se indica en el borrador del Programa del PCUS.</p>

<p>Son estas direcciones las que constituyen el contenido de la nueva ciencia de la gestión óptima de los sistemas complejos, llamada cibernética. Como se ha indicado anteriormente y se describe con más detalle en los artículos de esta colección, la principal tarea de la cibernética es desarrollar esos nuevos métodos y utilizar esos nuevos medios científicos y técnicos para gestionar la economía nacional, los procesos de producción y la investigación científica, lo que permitiría alcanzar el objetivo con el menor tiempo, mano de obra, material y consumo de energía. Ese régimen de gestión se suele denominar óptimo.</p>

<p>Hablando en la Conferencia de toda la Unión de Trabajadores de la Ciencia el 12 de junio de 1961, el Presidente de la Academia de Ciencias de la URSS acad. M. V. Keldysh dijo: “Hasta ahora, no hemos tenido un alcance suficiente de trabajo en el campo de la cibernética: la ciencia de los procesos de control, que actualmente es de importancia práctica y teórica primaria. La investigación en esta área debe intensificarse y combinarse en el instituto apropiado o en el consejo de coordinación especial “. Estamos totalmente de acuerdo con esta declaración.</p>

<p>Los autores de esta colección, los editores y la Editorial Estatal de Literatura Energética desean que su trabajo contribuya a resolver las tareas asignadas a la cibernética soviética. Consideramos que nuestra tarea principal es poner esta nueva ciencia al servicio de la construcción más temprana posible de una sociedad comunista en nuestro país. El segundo y el tercer volumen de nuestra colección, que planeamos publicar en 1962 y 1963, servirán para esta tarea.</p>

<p>Los científicos de la Unión Soviética, sin duda, harán todo lo posible para justificar la confianza de nuestro partido y la tremenda asistencia que brinda a la ciencia en nuestro país. En su trabajo diario, serán guiados por los maravillosos pensamientos expuestos en el borrador del Programa:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>El progreso de la ciencia y la tecnología en las condiciones de un sistema económico socialista permite el uso más eficiente de la riqueza y la naturaleza de la naturaleza en interés de las personas, para descubrir nuevos tipos de energía, crear nuevos materiales, desarrollar métodos para influir en las condiciones climáticas y dominar el espacio exterior. La aplicación de la ciencia se convierte en un factor decisivo en el poderoso crecimiento de las fuerzas productivas de la sociedad. El desarrollo de la ciencia y la introducción de sus logros en la economía nacional seguirá siendo de particular interés para el partido.</p>
</blockquote>

<hr>

<h2 id="heading-notas">Notas</h2>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>NdT: Obras completas de V. I. Lenin, 4ª ed., Gospolitizdat, 1950. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">↩</a> <a href="#fnref:1:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">↩<sup>2</sup></a> <a href="#fnref:1:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">↩<sup>3</sup></a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>NdT: Pravda, “La Verdad”, órgano de expresión del PCUS. <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">↩</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>NdT: El concepto de “información” fue problemático en el marxismo dogmático del estalinismo. Para el materialismo mal entendido de los censores estalinistas, una cosa que no era materia ni energía solo podía ser un delirio idealista y burgués. Esto explica la cautela con la que Berg trata este tema, tratando de alejar el foco de atención de su la definición con una audaz comparación entre la información, el tiempo y el espacio, para los cuales “no tenemos una definición exacta” pero los “medimos perfectamente con gran precisión”. <a href="#fnref:3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">↩</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:4" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>NdT: Editorial Estatal de Literatura Energética. <a href="#fnref:4" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">↩</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:5" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>NdT: Periódico económico. <a href="#fnref:5" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">↩</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:6" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>NdT: Editorial Política Estatal. <a href="#fnref:6" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">↩</a> <a href="#fnref:6:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">↩<sup>2</sup></a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:7" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>NdT: Académico era el título de los miembros honorarios de una academia de ciencias de la Unión Soviética, uno de los rangos más altos a nivel científico. <a href="#fnref:7" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">↩</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:8" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>S. N. Braines, A. V. Napalkov, V. B. Svechinsky, Notas científicas de la Academia de Ciencias Médicas de la URSS, Instituto de Psiquiatría, “Problemas de Neurocibernética”, 1959. <a href="#fnref:8" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">↩</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:9" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>NdT: Candidato de ciencias (Кандидат наук) es un título equivalente al doctorado. <a href="#fnref:9" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">↩</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:10" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>NdT: La <a href="https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paidolog%C3%ADa" class="link-wikipedia">paidología</a> es una rama de la psicología dedicada al estudio del comportamiento de los niños, a diferencia de la <a href="https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pedagog%C3%ADa" class="link-wikipedia">pedagogía</a> que se dedica al estudio de los procesos de enseñanza y aprendizaje. <a href="#fnref:10" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">↩</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:11" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>NdT: Izdatelstvo fíziko-matematicheskói i tejnicheskói literatury, “Editorial para la literatura físico-matemática y técnica. <a href="#fnref:11" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">↩</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:12" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>NdT: El <em>Symposium on Mechanisation of Thought Processes</em> fue el primer simposio internacional sobre inteligencia artificial, donde acudieron pioneros de este campo como Marvin L. Minsky o John McCarthy (el autor del término “inteligencia artificial”). La inteligencia artificial, propuesta en el encuentro de Darthmouth en 1956 y discutida en el simposio de Teddington en 1958, tuvo una coexistencia difícil con la cibernética. Posteriormente, los proponentes de la inteligencia artificial conseguirían acaparar la financiación para sus proyectos, <a href="https://lamaquinadeturing.su/2020/05/01/cuando-la-inteligencia-artificial-desplazo-la-cibernetica/" class="link-external">desterrando la cibernética hacia otros campos como las ciencias sociales</a>. <a href="#fnref:12" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">↩</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:13" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>NdT: Quizá la International Conference for Standards on a Common Language for Machine Searching and Translation celebrada en la Western Reserve University, Cleveland. <a href="#fnref:13" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">↩</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:14" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>NdT: Economía Planificada. <a href="#fnref:14" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">↩</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Cibernética" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[El siguiente texto es una traducción de la introducción al primer volumen de “Cibernética – al servicio del comunismo”, editado por Aksel I. Berg en 1961 en la URSS después de la restauración política de esta disciplina científica, antes demonizada por el estalinismo.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://lamaquinadeturing.su/cybernetics.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://lamaquinadeturing.su/cybernetics.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry xml:lang="ca"><title type="html">Quan la intel·ligència artificial va desplaçar la cibernètica</title><link href="https://lamaquinadeturing.su/ca/2020/05/quan-la-intelligencia-artificial-va-desplacar-la-cibernetica/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Quan la intel·ligència artificial va desplaçar la cibernètica" /><published>2020-05-01T10:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-01T10:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://lamaquinadeturing.su/ca/2020/05/quan-la-intelligencia-artificial-va-desplacar-la-cibernetica</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lamaquinadeturing.su/ca/2020/05/quan-la-intelligencia-artificial-va-desplacar-la-cibernetica/"><![CDATA[<p><em>Fragment de</em> On the Importance of Being Emergent <em>de Peter Cariani<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. En la pugna entre els fundadors de la intel·ligència artificial contra els defensors de la cibernètica, cal entendre que el paradigma dominant de la IA fins als anys 80 era el de les representacions simbòliques dels problemes, i per tant descartava mètodes com l’aprenentatge autònom i les xarxes neuronals, basats en el processament estadístic i contemplat per la cibernètica, que irònicament avui dia és el que més s’associa a la intel·ligència artificial.</em></p>

<hr>

<p>Al meu entendre, l’error més exasperant que cometen els editors [d’<em>Emergence and Embodiment</em>] és confondre la cibernètica primerenca amb la IA simbòlica i la informàtica (com en la primera frase del teaser a la contraportada del llibre). Els “aspectes matemàtics i d’enginyeria de la cibernètica” es caracteritzen com a “Intel·ligència Artificial (IA), robòtica, informàtica i tecnologies de comandament, control i comunicacions” (pp. 34–35). Tot i que la cibernètica primerenca va incloure la teoria de control adaptatiu i algunes robòtiques (les tortugues autònomes de George Walter), la cibernètica era i és bastant diferent de la informàtica i la IA (“IA simbòlica”). Aquests moviments tenen objectius, conceptes i mètodes fonamentalment diferents – la cibernètica es refereix a l’organització d’acció efectiva en el món a través de la incorporació de fins en els mitjans, no les possibilitats computacionals i representacionals dels sistemes de símbols – però l’afany sembla ser barrejar tot en una “tecnociència” infocomputacional que ens ha donat “un ordinador al teu escriptori i un iPhone a la teva butxaca” (p. 35). Quan molts comentaristes de teoria cultural confonen la cibernètica amb simulacions de vida artificial, autòmats cel·lulars, estudis de complexitat i l’emergència computacional <em>à la</em> Wolfram, hom té la sensació que les profundes diferències filosòfiques entre la cibernètica i aquests enfocaments computacionalistes d’avui dia són poc apreciats.</p>

<p>L’antagonisme, tant filosòfic com financer, entre la cibernètica i la IA sembla història oblidada. La IA va néixer en una conferència a dartmouth el 1956 que va ser organitzada per McCarthy, Minsky, Rochester i Shannon, tres anys després que les conferències de Macy sobre cibernètica haguessin acabat (Boden 2006; McCorduck 1972). Els dos moviments van coexistir durant aproximadament una dècada, però a mitjans de la dècada de 1960, els defensors de la IA simbòlica van obtenir el control dels canals de finançament nacional i van desfinançar la recerca en cibernètica. Això va liquidar eficaçment els subcamps de sistemes autoorganitzadors, xarxes neuronals i màquines adaptatives, programació evolutiva, computació biològica i biònica durant diverses dècades, deixant als treballadors en gestió, teràpia i ciències socials mantenir viva la flama. Crec que algunes de les polèmiques entre teòrics de control de primer ordre i multituds de segon ordre que vaig presenciar en dècades posteriors van ser el resultat acumulatiu d’un canvi de finançament, pertinença i recerca de les ciències naturals “dures” a les intervencions sociopsicològiques “toves”. Les guerres de clans es produeixen quan disminueix la reserva de recursos naturals. En lloc de files d’estàtues gegantines de moai als turons de Nowbarren, ens hem deixat biblioteques d’escrits monumentals sobre idees profundes els significats originals de les quals s’estan perdent ràpidament amb el temps.</p>

<hr>

<h2 id="heading-notes">Notes</h2>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>Cariani P. <em>On the Importance of Being Emergent. Extended Review of “Emergence and Embodiment: New Essays on Second-Order Systems Theory”.</em> Duke University Press, Durham, 2009. Constructivist Foundations 5(2): 86-91. 2010. Traduït de <a href="http://constructivist.info/5/2/086.cariani" class="link-external">l’original</a>. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">↩</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Cibernètica" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Fragment de On the Importance of Being Emergent de Peter Cariani1. En la pugna entre els fundadors de la intel·ligència artificial contra els defensors de la cibernètica, cal entendre que el paradigma dominant de la IA fins als anys 80 era el de les representacions simbòliques dels problemes, i per tant descartava mètodes com l’aprenentatge autònom i les xarxes neuronals, basats en el processament estadístic i contemplat per la cibernètica, que irònicament avui dia és el que més s’associa a la intel·ligència artificial. Cariani P. On the Importance of Being Emergent. Extended Review of “Emergence and Embodiment: New Essays on Second-Order Systems Theory”. Duke University Press, Durham, 2009. Constructivist Foundations 5(2): 86-91. 2010. Traduït de l’original. ↩]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://lamaquinadeturing.su/darthsmouth.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://lamaquinadeturing.su/darthsmouth.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry xml:lang="es"><title type="html">Cuando la inteligencia artificial desplazó la cibernética</title><link href="https://lamaquinadeturing.su/es/2020/05/cuando-la-inteligencia-artificial-desplazo-la-cibernetica/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cuando la inteligencia artificial desplazó la cibernética" /><published>2020-05-01T10:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-01T10:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://lamaquinadeturing.su/es/2020/05/cuando-la-inteligencia-artificial-desplazo-la-cibernetica</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lamaquinadeturing.su/es/2020/05/cuando-la-inteligencia-artificial-desplazo-la-cibernetica/"><![CDATA[<p><em>Fragmento de</em> On the Importance of Being Emergent <em>de Peter Cariani<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. En la pugna entre los fundadores de la inteligencia artificial contra los defensores de la cibernética, cabe entender que el paradigma dominante de la IA hasta los años 80 era el de las representaciones simbólicas de los problemas, y por lo tanto descartaba métodos como el aprendizaje autónomo y las redes neuronales, basados en el procesado estadístico y contemplado por la cibernética, que irónicamente hoy en día es el que más se asocia a la inteligencia artificial.</em></p>

<hr>

<p>En mi opinión, el error más exasperante que cometen los editores [de <em>Emergence and Embodiment</em>] es mezclar la cibernética temprana con la IA simbólica y la informática (como en la primera frase del adelanto de la contraportada del libro). Los “aspectos matemáticos y de ingeniería de la cibernética” se caracterizan como “Inteligencia Artificial (IA), robótica, informática y tecnologías de mando-control-comunicación” (pp. 34–35). Aunque la cibernética temprana abarcaba la teoría del control adaptativo y algo de robótica (las tortugas autónomas de Grey Walter), la cibernética era y es bastante distinta de la informática y la IA (“IA simbólica”). Estos movimientos tienen objetivos, conceptos fundadores y métodos fundamentalmente diferentes – la cibernética se refiere a la organización de acciones efectivas en el mundo a través de la incorporación de fines en los medios, no las posibilidades computacionales y de representación de los sistemas de símbolos – pero el impulso parece ser el de agrupar crudamente todo en una “tecnociencia” info-computacional que nos ha dado “una computadora en tu escritorio y un iPhone en tu bolsillo” (p. 35). Cuando muchos comentaristas de la teoría cultural confunden la cibernética con las simulaciones de vida artificial, los autómatas celulares, los estudios de complejidad y el surgimiento computacional <em>à la</em> Wolfram, uno tiene la sensación de que las profundas diferencias filosóficas entre la cibernética y estos enfoques computacionales de los últimos tiempos son poco apreciadas.</p>

<p>El antagonismo, tanto filosófico como financiero, entre la cibernética y la IA parece haberse perdido en la historia. La inteligencia artificial nació en una conferencia celebrada en Dartmouth en 1956, organizada por McCarthy, Minsky, Rochester y Shannon, tres años después de que concluyeran las conferencias de Macy sobre cibernética (Boden 2006; McCorduck 1972). Los dos movimientos coexistieron durante aproximadamente una década, pero a mediados de la década de 1960, los defensores de la IA simbólica obtuvieron el control de los canales de financiación nacional y desfinanciaron despiadadamente la investigación cibernética. Esto efectivamente liquidó los subcampos de los sistemas autoorganizados, las redes neuronales y las máquinas adaptativas, la programación evolutiva, la computación biológica y la biónica durante varias décadas, dejando a los trabajadores de la gestión, la terapia y las ciencias sociales para mantener viva la llama. Creo que algunos de los polémicos forcejeos entre los teóricos del control de primer orden y las multitudes del segundo orden de los que fui testigo en décadas posteriores fueron el resultado acumulativo de un cambio en la financiación, la composición y la investigación desde las ciencias naturales “duras” a las intervenciones socio-psicológicas “blandas”. Las guerras de clanes se producen cuando la reserva de recursos naturales disminuye. En lugar de filas de gigantescas estatuas de moai en las colinas de Nowbarren, nos han dejado bibliotecas de escritos monumentales sobre ideas profundas cuyos significados originales se están perdiendo rápidamente en el tiempo.</p>

<hr>

<h2 id="heading-notas">Notas</h2>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>Cariani P. <em>On the Importance of Being Emergent. Extended Review of “Emergence and Embodiment: New Essays on Second-Order Systems Theory”.</em> Duke University Press, Durham, 2009. Constructivist Foundations 5(2): 86-91. 2010. Traducido del <a href="http://constructivist.info/5/2/086.cariani" class="link-external">original</a>. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">↩</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Cibernética" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Fragmento de On the Importance of Being Emergent de Peter Cariani1. En la pugna entre los fundadores de la inteligencia artificial contra los defensores de la cibernética, cabe entender que el paradigma dominante de la IA hasta los años 80 era el de las representaciones simbólicas de los problemas, y por lo tanto descartaba métodos como el aprendizaje autónomo y las redes neuronales, basados en el procesado estadístico y contemplado por la cibernética, que irónicamente hoy en día es el que más se asocia a la inteligencia artificial. Cariani P. On the Importance of Being Emergent. Extended Review of “Emergence and Embodiment: New Essays on Second-Order Systems Theory”. Duke University Press, Durham, 2009. Constructivist Foundations 5(2): 86-91. 2010. Traducido del original. ↩]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://lamaquinadeturing.su/darthsmouth.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://lamaquinadeturing.su/darthsmouth.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>